<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Instructions about right beleeving: severall sermons leading unto Christ, directing unto faith, and incouraging thereto. Shewing the nature, measure, and necessitie of the sense of sinne. Christ the bread of life, a sufficient remedy for mans misery; with the way and meanes to obtain him; as also incouragements to come to him, from his abilitie and readinesse to give full soule-satisfaction. / By John Archer, Master of Art, sometime preacher of All-hallowes Lumbard-street. London.</title>
            <author>Archer, John, Master of Art.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 179 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75538</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3613</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E289_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200123</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860927</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860927</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113054</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75538)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113054)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 48:E289[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Instructions about right beleeving: severall sermons leading unto Christ, directing unto faith, and incouraging thereto. Shewing the nature, measure, and necessitie of the sense of sinne. Christ the bread of life, a sufficient remedy for mans misery; with the way and meanes to obtain him; as also incouragements to come to him, from his abilitie and readinesse to give full soule-satisfaction. / By John Archer, Master of Art, sometime preacher of All-hallowes Lumbard-street. London.</title>
                  <author>Archer, John, Master of Art.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 77, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Benjamin Allen, and are to be sold at his shop, at the Crown in Popes-head-Alley.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London; :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Forgiveness of sin --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113054:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>INSTR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CTIONS</hi> ABOUT RIGHT BELEEVING: SEVERALL SERMONS Leading unto Chriſt, directing unto Faith, and incouraging thereto. <hi>Shewing the Nature, Meaſure, and neceſsitie of the ſenſe of Sinne.</hi> Chriſt the bread of Life, a ſufficient Remedy for Mans miſery; with the way and meanes to obtaine him; as alſo incouragements to come to him, from his abilitie and readineſſe to give full ſoule-ſatisfaction. By JOHN ARCHER, Maſter of Art, ſometime Preacher of <hi>All-hallowes Lumbard-ſtreet.</hi> London.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>ACTS 2. 39.</bibl> 
               <hi>Now when they heard this, they were pricked in their heart.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>MAT. 11. 28.</bibl> 
               <hi>Come unto me all ye that labour &amp; are heavie laden, and I will give you reſt.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>JOHN 4. 14.</bibl> 
               <hi>Whoſoever drinketh of the water that I ſhall give him, ſhall never thirſt: but the water that I ſhall give him, ſhall be in him a Well of water ſpringing up into everlaſting life.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed for <hi>Benjamin Allen,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop, at the Crown in <hi>Popes-head-Alley.</hi> 1645.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:113054:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:113054:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>GOOD READER;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onſidering the ſtate of moſt people to be, either wholy inſenſible of their miſerable eſtate, and goe on ſecurely, not minding the precious and ſoule-ſaving Remedy tendred, or ſome others who are ſenſible, who are oft diſcouraged, (both, through the malice and ſubtiltie of the Devill,) theſe enſuing Sermons, in a plaine and profitable way, tending to helpe, in both theſe reſpects, are here preſented for a farre more publick advantage, then they could be in the preaching of them; They are not corrected and fitted for the Preſſe, as it were to be wiſhed, but neere the matter, and way of his delivery: and the experience had of ſome mens Sermons ſo printed, hath incouraged to theſe, conceiving they will be
<pb facs="tcp:113054:3"/> profitable, hoping all will be ſo charitable as to put good conſtructions, and not by the contrary, prejudice themſelves, or others from the good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended: Some things are but briefly propounded, in the Cloſe, but there are ſevcrall things profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly opened, to direct ſinners to Chriſt, and incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage ſenſible ones to come to him, with incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſo to doe, ſhewing his fitneſſe and ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency for their helpe, and readineſſe to it, and the Soule-ſatisfaction to be had by him: All which is here commended to thee, for thy good, in deſire, and with deſire of which, and of thy amending what eſcapes thou meeteſt with, I leave thee, and it, to the bleſſing of God.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113054:3"/>
            <head>CHRIST IS THE <hi>BREAD of LIFE.</hi> A SUFFICIENT REMEDY, FOR <hi>MANS MISERY.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>John. 6. 35.</bibl> And Ieſus ſaid unto them, I am the bread of life: he that commeth to mee ſhall never hunger; and he that beleeveth on me ſhall never thirſt.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HESE WORDS, are an <hi>Anſwer</hi> to that <hi>Deſire</hi> or <hi>Demand</hi> of the People in the former Verſe, <hi>Lord, evermore give us this bread:</hi> Wherein <hi>Chriſt</hi> opens to them, What is that <hi>Bread,</hi> which they ſeemed to deſire; Which <hi>Words</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> I will Conſider ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely in themſelves; and paſſe what may be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from their Coherence, &amp; Dependence; and will not ſtand on every thing which may be Collected fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Verſe,</hi> but ſo much as may ſerve for my purpoſe; Which is This:</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:113054:4"/>
            <p>Having ſhewed you the Miſery you are in by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and how far you muſt be humbled with the ſence <note place="margin">The Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of the Wordes.</note> of it; Now I ſhall ſhew ye the <hi>Remedy,</hi> and by what <hi>Meanes</hi> it may be attained: For which purpoſe this <hi>Verſe</hi> is very full. In which you have:</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt a <hi>Diſcription</hi> of <hi>Christ:</hi> Which is done Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorically by Bread; <hi>I am the Bread of Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly the <hi>Meanes</hi> by which this <hi>Chriſt</hi> may be had; Viz: <hi>By comming to Him;</hi> That is (as its expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) <hi>By beleeving on Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly the <hi>Perſons</hi> who may doe this, and ſo make <hi>Chriſt</hi> their owne; Viz: <hi>Any One whoever;</hi> as is implyed in the indefinite propounding of it; <hi>He that commeth, He that beleeveth.</hi> (as ye ſhall ſee more clearly heerafter)</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly a <hi>ſtrong Motive</hi> to perſwade to labour for this <hi>Chriſt,</hi> taken from the Benifitt; <hi>Shall never hunger, Shall never thirſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <p>FIRST, The <hi>Deſcription of Chriſt;</hi> which is Metaphorically; <hi>The Bread of Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="doctrine">
                  <head>DOCTRINE. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                     </label> 
                  </head>
                  <q>CHRIST is the BREAD of LIFE.</q>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Opened by anſwer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing divers Queſtions.</note>This is oft repeated in this <hi>Chapter:</hi> And for ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of which. Conſider theſe <hi>Queſtions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion. </seg>1</label> Firſt, <hi>What is ment, By Bread of Life.</hi> 
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
                     </label> I Anſwer; whatever is needfull, &amp; ſufficient, to bring People out of that Miſery they are in by Sinne, to that Happynes they loſt in Adam: <hi>A Sufficiency of Meanes.</hi> To <hi>Free from Miſery,</hi> And <hi>Bring to Happynes:</hi> As is more fully expreſt (though in other Metaphors) In <hi>Verſes</hi> 53, 54. of this <hi>Chapter; Except ye eate the flesh of the Sonne of man, and drinke his blood, ye have no life in you &amp;c.</hi> And
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113054:4"/> therefore <hi>Chriſt</hi> culls out a Metaphor, that is one of the cheife to ſupport Mans mortall Life; Viz: <hi>Bread;</hi> And therefore adds this Epithite; Of Life, That as Bread is ſpecially uſefull for our Life; <hi>So is Chriſt</hi> for the <hi>Spirituall &amp; Eternall Life;</hi> The <hi>Bread of Life,</hi> That is the <hi>Remedy</hi> of Mans miſery, in which he is by Nature &amp; Sinne.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion. </seg>2</label> Secondly, <hi>Whether this be proper to Chriſt, Or common with him to ſome other?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
                     </label> I Anſwer it is proper to <hi>Him;</hi> Nothing elſe, nether in whole, nor in part, hath any ſhare in it (except as his Inſtruments) Theſe Words <hi>[I am the Bread of Life]</hi> are not onely declarative of what <hi>He is,</hi> but <hi>impropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> and reſtraining this, <hi>to Him onely;</hi> This is the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; That <hi>He,</hi> and <hi>He onely</hi> is the <hi>Bread of Life:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that <hi>Verſe.</hi> 53. <hi>Except ye eate Him ye have noe Life;</hi> Therefore, <hi>He onely, is the Bread of Life.</hi> And <hi>Gen:</hi> 3. 15. <hi>The ſeede of the Woman</hi> (that is Chriſt) <hi>ſhall breake the Serpents head;</hi> That is, recover Man out of Miſery; <hi>God</hi> never promiſed it ſhould be, but <hi>Onely by Him,</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by <hi>Him onely</hi> it ſhall be; And ſo much is expreſt by that, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 6. 67. 68. <hi>Ieſus ſaid unto the twelue, will ye alſo goe away? Then Simon Peter anſwered him Lord, to whome ſhall we goe? Thou haſt the Words of Eternall Life;</hi> If <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Life</hi> could have been had by any other, then they <hi>might have gone away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt;</hi> that reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had not been ſtrong; And this is expreſſe by that, <hi>Acts.</hi> 4 12. <hi>Neither is there Salvation in any other: For there is none other Name under Heaven given among men, whereby we muſt be ſaved.</hi> As the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the <hi>Willdernes</hi> had noe helpe from the deadly ſtings of <hi>fiery Serpents,</hi> but by the <hi>Braſen Serpent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, <hi>By what Meanes; Chriſt comes to be bread of Life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:113054:5"/>
                  <p>I Anſwer, by His Incarnation, and all that He did &amp; ſuffered, till He ſate downe at <hi>Gods right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in Glory:</hi> All this, was for the fiting &amp; making <hi>Him bread of Life;</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">How Chriſt comes to be Bread of Life.</note> as <hi>Chriſt</hi> came into the World for this end, to become <hi>Bread of Life;</hi> So all <hi>He did &amp; ſuffered,</hi> in comming into, and being in, the World, till <hi>He</hi> was tranſlated out of it, and ſet downe in Glory, was for this end. As:</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. His Incarnation, or joyning together of both Natures, the <hi>Divine &amp; Humane,</hi> in <hi>One Perſon</hi> was for to make him fit to be this <hi>Bread of Life;</hi> Therefore <hi>Chriſt,</hi> being about to ſhew <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> that <hi>Eternall Life</hi> might be had by <hi>Him, Iohn.</hi> 3. 15. That is, that <hi>He was the bread of Life;</hi> He firſt ſhewes him his Incarnation, &amp; double Nature; <hi>Verſe</hi> 14. <hi>That as Moſes lifted up the Serpent in the Wildernes: Even ſo muſt the Sonne of man be lifted up:</hi> For as Bread is not made of one ſingle ſubſtance, but of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall, joyned together; So <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Bread of Life;</hi> the <hi>Man-hood</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> could not be effectuall to bring us to <hi>Life;</hi> without the <hi>God-head;</hi> being neither of Power enough to ſtand under, and come forth, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that Wrath it muſt undergoe; Nor of Vertue enough to make its Actions &amp; Suffrings of infinite worth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which an infinite debt could not be paid; And the <hi>God-head,</hi> though in it <hi>Selfe</hi> its a <hi>Fountaine of Life,</hi> &amp; very Communicative, being infinitely Good, Yet by Sinne; <hi>Its</hi> ſealed up, and becomes terrible &amp; a conſuming fire, So that <hi>It</hi> Conveyes nothing but Wrath &amp; De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; But the <hi>Man-hood,</hi> makes it an <hi>Open Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,</hi> ſatisfying &amp; appeaſing of <hi>It Heb.</hi> 10. 19. to 23. Thus; <hi>Chriſts</hi> Incarnation &amp; Union of two Natures, Viz: The <hi>God-head &amp; Man-hood</hi> in <hi>One Perſon;</hi> prepares and fits <hi>Him</hi> to be <hi>Bread of Life.</hi> And:</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, His naturall Infirmities, &amp; outward
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113054:5"/> Meaneſſe, and all His Sufferings, were to fit Him for this; As Corne, is threſhed, ground, baked in the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, before it makes Bread. <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 14. 21 22. Theſe, appeaſed <hi>Gods Wrath,</hi> and ſatisfied <hi>His Iuſtice,</hi> for our Sinnes, by which, we were Condemned:</p>
                  <p>And ſo, His Obedience &amp; Fulfilling of the Law; This prepared a <hi>Robe to cover us,</hi> by vertue of which, <hi>Wee might appeare ſpotles in Gods ſight, Rev</hi> 19. 8. And:</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, His Reſurrection, was alſo to fit Him to be <hi>Bread of Life;</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 17 <hi>And if Christ be not raiſed, your faith is vaine, ye are yet in your ſinnes.</hi> As Bread comes out of the Oven in which it is baked, Or elſe cannot preſerve our Life. And:</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, His Aſcenſion &amp; ſiting downe in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, was alſo to fit Him to be <hi>Bread of Life;</hi> This in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed was the laſt preparative Thing he did, and but an Introduction, or letting Him into that place &amp; Condition, wherein He might doe the Worke of <hi>Bread of Life,</hi> who was now by former things, made fully, Compleate <hi>Bread of Life:</hi> Yet this alſo was done as a Concurrence to His being <hi>Bread of Life;</hi> For before He could be <hi>given as Bread,</hi> and <hi>worke as Bread,</hi> He muſt be aſcended Heaven and ſet downe there; Therefore he ſaith He muſt aſcend <hi>That the Spirit might come, Iohn.</hi> 16. 7. And <hi>Ehp.</hi> 4. 8. Aſcending up <hi>He gave Gifts unto Men;</hi> As Bread, deſcends into the Stomack and ſo ſends vertue &amp; ſtrength into the Body, before it can nouriſh &amp; preſerve Life.</p>
                  <p>Thus ye ſee, how <hi>Chriſt</hi> comes to be <hi>Bread of Life;</hi> And how many Things were to be done, to fit <hi>Him:</hi> And though before he dyed; <hi>He ſaid all was finished;</hi> He meanes not every thing, (for then why dyed he) But all that was to be done, before He gave up the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113054:6"/> Ghoſt; And therefore he proceeded to doe that, And therefore, None but <hi>He</hi> can be it, becauſe none elſe <note place="margin">Two Things to be gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> have, nor can have all theſe neceſſary Quallifications. And hence ye may farther gather Two Things.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. When <hi>Chriſt</hi> is actually <hi>The bread of Life;</hi> namely in his ſtate of Glory, then, when he is exalted &amp; at Gods right Hand; All the tyme &amp; ſtate of his Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation was to fitt &amp; prepare him to be <hi>bread of Life, Heb.</hi> 7. 25. 26. <hi>Now he is made higher then the Heavens, he is able to ſave to the uttermoſt;</hi> And <hi>Iohn.</hi> 14. 19. <hi>Now he lives</hi> (Viz: that glorious Life in Heaven) <hi>they ſhall live.</hi> And whereas He gave Life to many, before he had done theſe things (namely, to all Beleevers before he came) yet it was by vertue of all theſe, done in Gods account (becauſe ſurely to be done) and in Gods ſight to whome all things to come, aſwell as paſt, are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; <hi>Acts.</hi> 15. 18. <hi>Knowne unto God are all his Workes from the beginning of the World. Rev.</hi> 13. 8. <hi>The Lambe ſlaine from the foundation of the World.</hi> And:</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Ye may hence gather; what in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> Is the <hi>Bread of Life;</hi> Or how <hi>Chriſt</hi> muſt be conſidered &amp; applyed for <hi>Bread:</hi> Namely thus; The <hi>Man-hood</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with all that which it hath Done &amp; Suffred, &amp; conſequently out of Merrit received as into a ſtore houſe; <hi>Is the bread of Life;</hi> Therefore he ſaith <hi>His Flesh is meate &amp; his Blood is drinke indeed Iohn.</hi> 6: 35. It is true; that the <hi>Man-hood</hi> ſingly conſidered without Perſonall Union with the <hi>God head,</hi> is not <hi>This bread of Life</hi> (for then it is not of vertue enough, as ye heard before) But, the <hi>Man-hood,</hi> as it is in Perſonall Union with the <hi>God-head;</hi> and ſo made of Infinite Worth &amp; Vertue; So, the <hi>Man-hood</hi> is the <hi>Bread of Life;</hi> 1, <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 30. <hi>He of God, is made;</hi> that muſt be ment of <hi>his Man-hood</hi> (though
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113054:6"/> as it is in Perſonall Union with the <hi>God head)</hi> For the <hi>God head</hi> cannot be made a Communicated <hi>Wiſdome, Righteouſnes &amp;c.</hi> as that is; <hi>God</hi> joyned in Perſon with <hi>Chriſts Man-hood,</hi> hath by the Doings, Suffrings, and Merrits of the <hi>Man-hood,</hi> to which it was inabled by the <hi>God-head;</hi> furnished that <hi>Man-hood,</hi> with all <hi>Suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency,</hi> to free from Miſery and make Happy: Its not <hi>Chriſts God-head</hi> but <hi>His Man hood</hi> which is in Union with <hi>His God-head,</hi> and ſo a Vertue &amp; Effect of the <hi>God-head,</hi> and that which is in <hi>His Man-hood,</hi> that is the <hi>Bread of Life:</hi> Heere be Two Errors to be avoyded.</p>
                  <p>One when the <hi>God-head</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall be made the <note place="margin">Errors to be avoyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> 
                     <hi>Bread of Life;</hi> and that which is applyed by <hi>Faith,</hi> and made <hi>One with us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Another, when the <hi>Man-hood</hi> ſhall be ſimply Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, and not as it is in Perſonall Union with the <hi>God-head,</hi> and receives Vertue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, to make its Acts of Infinite Worth.</p>
                  <p>And thus by <hi>Faith</hi> we eate this <hi>Bread;</hi> whilſt we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, apply &amp; truſt in <hi>Christs Man hood,</hi> that which he did &amp; ſuffred in &amp; by it (through Union with the <hi>God-head)</hi> for our Juſtification, Sanctification, and Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and by <hi>Faith,</hi> we eate not his <hi>God-head,</hi> but <hi>Man-hood,</hi> and the Vertue of the <hi>God-head,</hi> that is in <hi>his Man-hood;</hi> And thus, that Queſtion; <hi>Iohn.</hi> 6. 52. is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, <hi>How Chriſt can give us his flesh to eate.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="1" type="application">
                  <head>1. USE, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> 
                  </head>
                  <p>To teach us; <hi>How much</hi> we owe to <hi>God &amp; Chriſt;</hi> who hath provided <hi>Bread</hi> for our <hi>Soules;</hi> as the <hi>Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> did to <hi>God</hi> for that <hi>Gen:</hi> 50. 20. <hi>For by this he ſaves ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Soules alive:</hi> God was oft magnified for the <hi>Manna</hi> he ſent for the <hi>Iſraellites</hi> when they were ready to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113054:7"/> periſh for hunger: This is more Mercy: Therefore, that, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3. 16. <hi>God ſo loved the World;</hi> So, as cannot be immitated; So, as cannot be expreſt; So, as cannot be conceived.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Mercy</hi> farther appeares; If we Conſider, that (which alſo this <hi>Doctrine</hi> teacheth us) it coſt <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſomewhat before they helped Soules; <hi>Chriſt muſt be bread;</hi> That is not his up &amp; doing it; But much muſt he doe and indure, before he was fited for it; As Bread doth before it become Bread; Therefore, we are the more bound to <hi>Him</hi> for his undertaking the Worke of <hi>Our Redemption:</hi> And to <hi>God</hi> the <hi>Father,</hi> For <hi>Giving Him</hi> to that Worke; If a King ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point his Sonne, and his Sonne undertake, to ſave Traytors, onely by comming to the Priſon &amp; fetching them out, it were worthy of much Thankes; But much more, when the Sonne, by much paines and coſt, ſhall doe it; <hi>Ioſeph</hi> procured Bread for <hi>Egypt,</hi> But <hi>Cbriſt was made Bread.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="application">
                  <head>2. USE, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                  </head>
                  <p>For <hi>Incouragement</hi> to Such as droope in the Sence of their Miſery, and want of Life; I may ſay to ſuch of you, as be amazed with the Sence of your Miſery by Sinne; As <hi>Iacob</hi> to his Sonnes, <hi>Gen.</hi> 42. 1. 2. <hi>Why doe ye looke one upon another? Behold I have heard that there is Corne in Egypt &amp;c.</hi> Whatever you want, whether <hi>Gods Favour,</hi> Or <hi>Image,</hi> The <hi>Life of Comfort,</hi> Or <hi>of Grace,</hi> deſpaire not; For <hi>God hath provided Bread for you;</hi> I, and ye need not be affraid to come to this <hi>Bread,</hi> and take it; For he loves to have People eate of <hi>Him;</hi> as will clearely appeare by this, which alſo followes from this Point, Viz: That <hi>Chriſt</hi> Came from Heaven for this
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113054:7"/> End, <hi>To recover Sinners out of their Miſery,</hi> And to helpe them to <hi>live;</hi> For that is the End of Bread; It is not directly for any other uſe; It is ſo of <hi>Chriſts Comming, Math.</hi> 18. 11. <hi>For the Sonne of Man is come to ſave that which was loſt: Iohn.</hi> 3. 17. <hi>For God ſent not his Sonne into the World to condemne the World. but that the World through Him might be ſaved:</hi> And <hi>Chap.</hi> 12. 47. <hi>I came not to judge the World, but to Save the World:</hi> Therefore they that feele their need of him, need not feare Comming to Him, or queſtion his helping of them: It was the End of His Comming, and the Uſe <hi>God</hi> cheifly put Him to: Therefore he will not be averſe from it; Hence it was in that, <hi>Math.</hi> 18. 11. Having told them that this was the <hi>End of His Comming,</hi> to <hi>Save;</hi> He, by a <hi>Parable</hi> ſhewes them what <hi>Ioy</hi> it was <hi>to Him to ſave any one;</hi> How can He but joy in making good the End of his Comming? Therefore, they that droope in a Sence of their Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and dare not goe to Chriſt for helpe, doe not knowe Chriſt, Nor the Miſtery of his Incarnation, Nor the End of his Comming; That it was to <hi>Releive the Afflicted;</hi> Learne it now therefore, and come confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently to <hi>Him</hi> for <hi>Helpe;</hi> He cannot but with all readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes <hi>entertaine thee,</hi> and the <hi>Opertunity</hi> of making good the End of his Comming; Therefore in Scripture, <hi>Christ</hi> was greedy of any opertunity to releive a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſed Soule; And <hi>did not quench the ſmoaking flax &amp;c. Math.</hi> 20, moſt <hi>meeke,</hi> and <hi>gentle,</hi> and <hi>eaſily intreated;</hi> therefore a Dove ſate on him, in His firſt Inſtalement into his Office; This is a maine thing, that is taught in the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> and may be obſerved through the whole Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; that <hi>Chriſt</hi> with <hi>abundance</hi> of <hi>gentlencs &amp; willingnes,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained &amp; incouraged all that in ſincerity came to him for helpe; Feare not then Chriſts rejecting thee,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113054:8"/> ſo thou have a right deſire to him, but preſſe him, if he ſeeme to deny thee, as the Woman did <hi>Marke.</hi> 7, 27. 28. Let not want of Life, or Weakenes hinder thee, for he came to helpe ſuch; as bread is for the empty and weake, Therefore ſay ye as <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi> 16. 15. 16. <hi>This is the bread which the Lord hath given you to eate &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="application">
                  <head>3. USE. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>3</label> 
                  </head>
                  <p>To teach us, <hi>how much</hi> we ſhould <hi>eſteeme &amp; prize Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Labour for Him;</hi> even as hunger ſtarved people doe for Bread; <hi>Iſraell</hi> deſired a cruell Bondage for Breads ſake, <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. 3. the Egyptian bondage fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which they were freed; And they <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6. 24 26. How did they <hi>follow Chriſt,</hi> from one Coaſte to another, for <hi>Loaves?</hi> What did <hi>Egypt</hi> doe for Bread-Corne, (not Bread, nor fitted to their hands) <hi>Gen:</hi> 41. 55. <hi>They cryed to Pharaoh for bread;</hi> And <hi>Cap.</hi> 47. 14. <hi>They parted with all their Mony for bread;</hi> And <hi>Ver.</hi> 17. <hi>They parted with all their Cattle;</hi> And <hi>Ver.</hi> 20. <hi>They parted with their Land;</hi> And <hi>Ver.</hi> 23. <hi>They ſould Themſelves;</hi> Would ye ſo doe for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ye ſhould have him, <hi>Iſay.</hi> 55. 1. <hi>Ho every one that thirſteth, come yee to the waters, and he that hath no mony: come ye, buy &amp; eate, yea, come; buy wine &amp; milke without mony, and without price;</hi> and why ſhould ye not, ſince <hi>He is Bread,</hi> not bread corne, but ready fitted to your hands? How did all Nations flock to <hi>Egypt, Gen:</hi> 41. 57. Becauſe Bread Corne was there? And why, flock ye not to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſince <hi>He is the Bread of Life?</hi> Doe ye not manefeſtly give him the lye, who calls <hi>Himſelfe Bread?</hi> And yee who ſo much care for Bread (as if ye call it to mind) ye did lately in the Famine; yet prize not, not care to get <hi>Him:</hi> Though it may ſeeme, not deſirable, as Bread oft doth to Children, therefore when it is given them,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113054:8"/> they caſt it away, Yet conſider, the caſe of your Soules, <hi>hunger-ſtarved;</hi> And <hi>He;</hi> the <hi>Bread of Life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That I may quicken ye up to prize &amp; eſteeme <hi>Chriſt</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Chriſt is better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any bread in many perticulers</note> more, Conſider, in how many Perticulers, <hi>He is better</hi> then any other Bread.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. Other Bread onely ſupports Life, it doth not give Life, (as ye all knowe) But <hi>Chriſt</hi> is a <hi>Bread</hi> that <hi>gives Life</hi> to them that <hi>be dead,</hi> and therefore is called the <hi>Bread of Life, Iohn.</hi> 6. 53. 54. 57.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Other Bread preſerves Life but for a while; <hi>Gen:</hi> 3. <hi>Eate it till thou turne to duſt,</hi> It doth but repreive as it were till an other Seſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s; It Corrupts, and keepes not the Body from Corrupting; But this <hi>Bread,</hi> gives <hi>Eternall Life. Iohn.</hi> 6. 50. 51. <hi>This is the Bread which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth downe from Heaven, that a man may eate thereof, and not dye; But live for ever;</hi> Therefore, <hi>Christ</hi> by this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument perſwades them to prefer this before other meate, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 6. 27. <hi>Labour not for the meate which perisheth, but for that meate which endureth unto everlaſting life, which the Sonne of man ſhall give unto you:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. Other Bread helpes but the Body in Point of Life, and but in an earthly Life; But this helps the <hi>Soule &amp; Body,</hi> and that in a <hi>Spirituall Life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4 Other Bread, is not enough to Life, but with that there muſt be other things, even in this ſence is that true <hi>Man lives not by bread alone,</hi> Therefore ye have <hi>Sampſon,</hi> not complaining of danger of Death, for want of Bread, but Water; But this <hi>Bread</hi> is <hi>Allſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent;</hi> It alayes Hunger &amp; Thirſt both, (as is in the Text) Yea, <hi>Its Wine, Milke, &amp; fat Things, Eſay.</hi> 55.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 5. Other Bread may be kept from you, or tooke from you when you need it, and uſually is rateſt to be had, when we moſt neede it, as in Famine; As Ponds
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113054:9"/> which be full in Winter, when we need no Water, but dry in Summer, when Water is moſt needed; But this <hi>Bread,</hi> None can keepe, nor take away, Its <hi>Ever free &amp; plentifully</hi> to be had.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 6. Other Bread, oft coſts deare, and is not every ones Mony, (as in Dearths) But the <hi>Price of This</hi> (as ye ſhall fee heerafter) is onely the <hi>Receiving it,</hi> the <hi>Comming, Taking,</hi> and <hi>Eating,</hi> (as its in our Text) and <hi>Its free for any,</hi> without reſtraint or limitation of Perſons.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 7. Other Bread may poſſibly have ſomewhat found in its roome that may ſerve Nature, though not all ſo well; But this <hi>Bread,</hi> can onely helpe our <hi>Soules,</hi> None elſe can but this, as ye heard in opening the <hi>Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine.</hi> So that without this, There is no <hi>Life</hi> to be had; Now Conſidering all theſe <hi>Super-excellencyes</hi> in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> Why ſhould ye not prize <hi>Him,</hi> and labour for <hi>Him</hi> more then for Bread? remember what you did for bread in the dearth, and doe <hi>more</hi> for <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="application">
                  <head>4. USE. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>4</label> 
                  </head>
                  <p>To teach us, <hi>That Chriſt is onely for hungry Soules</hi> Such as be <hi>ſenſible throughly</hi> of their <hi>Miſery</hi> by <hi>Sinne</hi> and ſo <hi>Pant after a Remedy;</hi> For, therefore he is called <hi>Bread,</hi> becauſe <hi>Its onely</hi> for the <hi>hungry:</hi> God hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided him onely for ſuch (as ye heard before from, <hi>Luke</hi> 5. 31 32.) as the Table is ſpread for the empty, not for the full; For indeed none elſe deſire, prize, or will receive him; pleaſant food is ſlighted by the full (even the hony combe) much more this, which is hard of digeſtion, and very groſſe to Fleſh &amp; Blouds pallat &amp; eye: Therefore, obſerve in Scripture, who they were that ſo <hi>Prized Chriſt;</hi> they were Soules, <hi>hunger</hi>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:113054:9"/> 
                     <hi>bitten</hi> with the <hi>ſence</hi> of their <hi>ſpirituall Miſery:</hi> And, who did ſlight him? Who were they to whome God never gave him? the Phariſees &amp; blind People, who were not hungry after a ſpirituall Mercy, as not being throughly ſenſible of a ſpirituall Miſery: And this is the very reaſon, why <hi>Chriſt</hi> is ſo litle regarded in the World; When one lookes in the Scripture and ſees what Excellent Things are ſpoke of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and on the longing deſires, the <hi>Saints</hi> of old had after <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and their abundant joy in <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and looke now how ſlightly &amp; by how few he is eſteemed; one would thinke that which is writ of them is fabulous; or they were fooliſh, or our <hi>Chriſt</hi> is not the ſame <hi>Chriſt;</hi> or why ſhould he then be longed for; and now, being co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me and offred is deſpiſed? But he ere is the truth of it; <hi>He is Bread,</hi> and they were <hi>hungry;</hi> But now moſt are full; Full with their Sinnes, their Honours, Profits, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of this World; and therefore care not for <hi>Chriſt;</hi> And mervaile at the <hi>hunger bitten Soules,</hi> which keepe ſuch a doe for <hi>Christ;</hi> But let all ſuch knowe, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is not as yet for them; <hi>God</hi> never prepared, appointed, or ſent him, for ſuch, but for the <hi>hungry;</hi> as the <hi>Shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bread</hi> was not for <hi>David himſelfe</hi> but in caſe of <hi>great hunger, Math.</hi> 12. 3. 4.</p>
                  <p>If <hi>God</hi> had immediatly &amp; ſuddenly conveyed <hi>Chriſt</hi> to ſinnfull Soules, then might he have been injoyed by you, without being <hi>firſt hungry;</hi> But ſince he gives him as <hi>Bread,</hi> you muſt ſo take him; that is <hi>firſt being hungry;</hi> This is the reaſon why many eate this <hi>Bread, Chriſt,</hi> and be never the better, becauſe they eate him without <hi>hunger firſt;</hi> and ſoe digeſt him not; but fill their Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les with crudy Humors, Security, Preſumption, &amp;c. which kill the Soule: Let an <hi>hungry Soule</hi> eate of this
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113054:10"/> 
                     <hi>Bread;</hi> it exceedingly ſtrengthens him to all Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, filling the Soule with good Nouriſhment &amp; Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, of Love, Peace, Hope, Joy: But if any that be not hungry doe eate of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> that is, apply him; <hi>He</hi> is to them, but as the foode to the <hi>Angells</hi> who were without ſtomacks <hi>Gen</hi> 18 8. they ſee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> eate, but eate not, and ſo were never the better for it though the foode was good. Hence the Soules of People be ſo ſtarveling like, though they oft injoy large Meales of this <hi>Bread,</hi> (Viz: the Word oft preacht, Sacraments oft adminiſtred) becauſe, wanting Stomacks they onely ſeeme to eate, but eate not. If therefore, ye <note place="margin">How to get a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, after Chriſt.</note> would be the better for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ye muſt get an <hi>Hunger,</hi> which that ye may the better doe.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. Diſgorge your Soules of that Surfet of Sinne &amp; earthly Vanityes, which ye have taken in; By Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the vanity &amp; hurtfullnes of them.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Get a ſtrong Appetite to <hi>Chriſt;</hi> Which is done, Partly by drinking downe the Vineger of the Law, eating the ſower Hearbs; By the Law laboring to ſee your Sinnfullnes &amp; Miſery thereby; And partly by looking into the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and <hi>Chriſts Beauty,</hi> and <hi>Deſirable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes;</hi> as <hi>Eve</hi> by Conſidering the Fruite, was drawne to take &amp; eate it: But I will not preſſe this, becauſe I have lately done it, and ſhewed you how farr you muſt be Humbled &amp; the Signes &amp; Meanes of it: All that I now ſay is this:</p>
                  <p>That as it was with the <hi>bitter Water</hi> in another ſence, So is it with <hi>Chriſt;</hi> If they that <hi>hunger,</hi> take &amp; eate him, they are <hi>ſaved by Him;</hi> If they that hunger <hi>not,</hi> medle with <hi>Him,</hi> It is their <hi>bane &amp; ruine:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thinke not thoſe Preachers your enemyes, who la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor to <hi>humble you</hi> by preſſing on you the Law, and your
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113054:10"/> miſerable Eſtate by Nature, for it is but to make you <hi>hungry,</hi> and ſo fit for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Bread of Life;</hi> We are your Paſtors &amp; Nurſes, and muſt ſeeke to get you Stomacks, that ye may eate, and not tread under foote this <hi>ſpirituall foode;</hi> therefore, thus, and for this end to ſeeke to <hi>humble you,</hi> is a part of our Duty &amp; Love to you; ſhould Preachers onely preach <hi>Chriſt</hi> to you, it would but delude you, for till you be <hi>hungry,</hi> God will not give him, nor will ye accept him, becauſe <hi>He is Bread.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus much for the Firſt Thing in the Text; The <hi>Deſcription of Chriſt;</hi> as the <hi>ſufficient Remedy of Mans Miſery.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <p>THE SECOND THING, in the TEXT, Is <note place="margin">The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Thing in the text.</note> the <hi>Meanes</hi> by which this <hi>Chriſt,</hi> This <hi>Remedy</hi> of our <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery,</hi> may be had: That is by <hi>Comming to Chriſt: He that comes to Me ſhall never hunger:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This, is farther expreſt in the Text, by an other word, Viz: <hi>Beleeving in him:</hi> So that <hi>comming to him,</hi> and <hi>beleeving on him,</hi> is all one and the ſame, and he that comes to Chriſt, or beleeves in Chriſt, ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Chriſt, and get him, for elſe he could not be kept from hungring &amp; thriſting, as the Text ſaith he ſhall be; And in other Scriptures, This (which is the <hi>Meanes</hi> by which <hi>Chriſt</hi> may be had) is expreſt in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther words; As <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1. 12. <hi>A receiving Chriſt;</hi> for there, receiving Chriſt &amp; beleeving on him, is made all one, and receiving Chriſt, is the meanes of geting Chriſt; (or elſe, he that receives him could not have preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to be <hi>Gods Sonne;</hi> as that Verſe affirmes of him) And elſe where; it is called a <hi>takeing, Reve.</hi> 22. 17.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:113054:11"/>
               <p>So that, the <hi>Meanes</hi> by which <hi>Chriſt</hi> (this <hi>Remedy</hi> of <hi>Mans miſery)</hi> may be had, is Comming to Him, Beleeving on Him, Taking or Receiving of Him: Hence obſerve.</p>
               <div type="doctrine">
                  <head>DOCTRINE. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                     </label> 
                  </head>
                  <q>The all &amp; onely MEANES of, and that GOD requires for, the Obtaining of CHRIST, and Salvation by CHRIST; Is the Comming to HIM, Taking, Receiving of HIM, or Beleev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on HIM.</q>
                  <p>This is expreſſe in the <hi>Texts,</hi> whence we now raiſe it, there is no more to be done, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> is injoyed, If <hi>God</hi> required more, or more muſt be done; Then this <hi>Verſe</hi> of my <hi>Text,</hi> doth not fully direct how to get the <hi>Bread of Life,</hi> But that it doth; Therefore, let a Man come to Chriſt, and he ſhall have Chriſt; This is all that God requires for the obtaining Chriſt; and therefore our <hi>Saviour,</hi> expreſſeth <hi>Chriſt</hi> by a <hi>Feaſt,</hi> ready prepared, and to be pertaked by all that come; <hi>Pro.</hi> 9. 1. 2. 3. <hi>Wiſdome hath builded her Houſe, She hath killed her Beaſts: She hath mingled her Wine: She hath furnished her Table, She hath ſent forth her Maydens, She cryeth: Who ſo is ſimple, let him turne in hither, She ſaith come eate of my Bread, and drinke of my Wine which I have mingled. Luke.</hi> 14. 17. <hi>He ſent his ſervant at ſupper time to ſay to them that were bidden; come, for all things are now ready;</hi> And they that eate not of it, miſte it becauſe they <hi>came not, Verſe</hi> 24. And however there was <hi>One</hi> that came, and yet was not permitted to eate at the <hi>Feaſt; Math.</hi> 22. 11. 12. 13. yet it followes not, that there is ſome what more required then Comming; for he miſcarried becauſe he <hi>came</hi>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:113054:11"/> 
                     <hi>not,</hi> had he come indeed; he had <hi>obtained;</hi> but he did but <hi>ſeeme</hi> to come, though it is called a Comming, for the want of the <hi>wedding garment,</hi> was onely a want of Comming, (as ye ſhall ſee heerafter, when we ſhew what <hi>Right comming</hi> is) This allſo is farther proved by theſe Scriptures, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 5. 40. <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. 37. <hi>Chap.</hi> 7. 37. <hi>&amp; Math.</hi> 11. 28.</p>
                  <p>And as the <hi>Scripture</hi> is expreſſe for the proofe of this; under the expreſſion of <hi>Comming;</hi> So alſo, is it as expreſſe; under the Phraſe of <hi>Beleeving; Math.</hi> 21. 31. <hi>The Publicans &amp; Harlots goe into the Kingdome of God before you:</hi> Why? For <hi>Verſe.</hi> 32. <hi>Yee beleeved not, but they did;</hi> Therefore <hi>Faith</hi> is the <hi>Way:</hi> Therefore when the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple askt <hi>Chriſt; What they ſhould doe to worke the Worke of God,</hi> that is to get <hi>Salvation,</hi> He preſcribes them this onely, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 6. 39. <hi>This is the Worke of God, that ye Beleeve:</hi> Hence; that, <hi>Marke.</hi> 16. 16. <hi>He that beleeveth ſhall be ſaved.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is taught by our <hi>Saviours</hi> making <hi>Faith</hi> the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument &amp; onely Meanes of Curing, &amp; Helping all them He cured in the Goſpel; and where He found not <hi>Faith,</hi> He did no great Cure; <hi>Math.</hi> 13 58.</p>
                  <p>Alſo, hence it is that Unbeleefe is made the onely Ground &amp; Reaſon of Mens Damnation; <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3. 18. 36. <hi>&amp; Chap.</hi> 8. 24. Though Men ſhall be puniſhed for all other Sinnes, Yet not Beleeving is the Ground &amp; Reaſon why they perish by their Sinnes; Becauſe <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving</hi> is the onely <hi>Meanes</hi> of <hi>Salvation:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And this was typified by the <hi>Iſralites</hi> not entering <hi>Canaan,</hi> becauſe of their Unbeleefe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp; laſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And hence alſo it is, that <hi>Beleeving,</hi> is in Scripture made the Fruite, Signe &amp; Pledge, of Gods ordaining People to <hi>Eternall Life, Acts.</hi> 13. 48. And not beleeving
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113054:12"/> is made the Fruite, &amp; Signe of Gods not purpoſing <hi>to Save People Iohn.</hi> 12, 39, 40. Becauſe, <hi>Beleeving is the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Meanes of obtaining Salvation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſtly, It is hence alſo, that all the <hi>Requiſites</hi> to <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> are made in <hi>Scripture</hi> the <hi>Conſequents &amp; Workes</hi> of <hi>Faith:</hi> Namely: The <hi>Righteouſnes</hi> of Chriſt for our <hi>Iuſtification, Rom:</hi> 3. 22. And the <hi>Spirit</hi> of Chriſt for our <hi>Sanctification: Gall.</hi> 3. 14.</p>
                  <p>Thus ye ſee, how the <hi>All</hi> and <hi>Onely Meanes</hi> of, and all that God requires for, <hi>Our obtaining Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Salvation</hi> by <hi>Him</hi> is to <hi>Come to Him,</hi> Or <hi>Beleeve on Him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And this was typified by the <hi>Braſen Serpent;</hi> as it is expounded &amp; applyed by <hi>Christ Iohn.</hi> 3. 14. as <hi>All</hi> that God required, and was the <hi>Meanes</hi> for obtaining Cure from the <hi>Braſen Serpent,</hi> was the <hi>Looking on it:</hi> as you may reade, <hi>Num:</hi> 21. 8. 9.</p>
                  <p>There are two <hi>Propoſitions,</hi> of neceſſity to be knowne by all that would be ſaved: One is, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the <hi>All &amp; onely Remedy of our Salvation;</hi> The other is, that <hi>Comming to Chriſt,</hi> or <hi>Beleeving on Him,</hi> is the <hi>All &amp; onely Meanes,</hi> whereby <hi>Chriſt ſaues us:</hi> There is no <hi>Salvation</hi> but by <hi>Chriſt onely;</hi> and there is no having <hi>Chriſt &amp; Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> but by <hi>Faith onely:</hi> As God conveyes Salvation <hi>onely</hi> by Chriſt; So Chriſt &amp; Salvation are had <hi>onely</hi> by Comming to, or Beleeving in Chriſt: The former of theſe, hath been taught you in the former Point; and now, the latter is as clearely taught.</p>
                  <p>For the better underſtanding, and making uſe of this <hi>Doctrine;</hi> It is fit to open &amp; ſhew; What this Comming to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> Receiving, Taking, and Beleeving on <hi>Him;</hi> is. They are (as ye heard before) ſeverall Words expreſſing one and the ſame Thing: And that is this.</p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:113054:12"/>
                  <p>The Act of the whole Man (that is of every part and faculty of Man) entertaining <hi>Chriſt</hi> offered in the <note place="margin">What com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to, and belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving on Chriſt, is.</note> 
                     <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and reſigning up himſelfe to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in all the <hi>Offices</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as a <hi>King, Preiſt, &amp; Prophet,</hi> to be ſaved by <hi>Him</hi> through thoſe <hi>Offices.</hi> To <hi>Beleeve in Chriſt;</hi> is not in Generall to phanſy &amp; conceite that I ſhall be ſaved by Chriſt and he dyed for me; as the Worlds Faith is.</p>
                  <p>Ye ſhall find Divines giving other deſcriptions of <hi>Faith.</hi> As namely, a perſwaſion of the forgivenes of my Sinnes &amp; Salvation of my Soule by Chriſt: Or a Confidence, &amp; Truſt in Chriſt for Salvation; which (with all other deſcriptions of <hi>Faith)</hi> I conceive to be <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Venire ad Chriſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt cum ſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torem reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere; &amp; ſe illi conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crare totum. Bucer in hunc locum.</hi> And ſee <hi>Bucer on Rom:</hi> 4. 3. <hi>in Malorets Comment.</hi>
                     </note> the expreſſions of ſome higher Degrees, Effects Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequents of <hi>Faith;</hi> and not to be the firſt act of <hi>Faith;</hi> But, as for this; which I have now given, ſo farr as I can find by Scripture, it is the firſt act of <hi>Faith,</hi> and that which truely gives title to, &amp; intereſt in, the <hi>Lord Ieſus</hi> and <hi>Salvation by Him;</hi> And being the firſt act; it may be, where other &amp; farther acts &amp; degrees of <hi>Faith,</hi> cannot preſently be found; This is it; which <hi>Bucer</hi> explaines the Comming to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to be; To Come to Chriſt (ſaith he) is to receive him for a <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,</hi> and to reſigne &amp; give up <hi>his whole ſelfe</hi> to him; <note place="margin">The eate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Bread, is by <hi>Faith</hi> to receive him, <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin.</hi>
                     </note> And therefore, I thinke, <hi>Beleeving</hi> is expreſt by the phraſes of <hi>comming to Him, taking receiving of Him;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is a ſo doing as is before deſcribed; For then (as any one in reaſon knowes) is <hi>Chriſt</hi> come to, tooke, and received, when he is entertained as <hi>He is,</hi> and as <hi>He is offered</hi> by <hi>God</hi> A <hi>King, Preiſt, &amp; Prophet;</hi> for the Ends for which <hi>God tenders Him;</hi> Viz: <hi>To be ſaved by Him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And whereas it may be objected; that the Word, <hi>Beleeving, in</hi> or <hi>on Chriſt;</hi> implyes a Confidence or
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113054:13"/> Truſt in him; a relying on him; I Anſwer it is moſt true; and therefore, the phraſe is extreordinary, not to be found (as ſome have obſerved) in any Writers, but the Scriptures, (and Such as take it from them) Others uſing onely this phraſe, to beleeve a thing; and not to beleeve in it, or on it; So that the phraſe implyes relying on it with a Confidence &amp; Expectation of the Thing. And ſo I thinke, that there never is, nor can be, a Comming to Chriſt, or Receiving him, without a Truſt, Confidence, or Relying on him: And the Comming to Him, or Receiving of Him, is the Effect of this; (for therefore, they Come to Him &amp; Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Him, becauſe they Truſt to be Helped by Him) but this may not allwayes be Evident, as the Cauſe is oft more obſcure then the Effect, And ſo, a Man may Entertaine Chriſt, when he thinks he cannot Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye on Him &amp; Truſt in Him:</p>
                  <p>But yet there is a double Truſting or Relying on Chriſt; The one is, at a Venture, without a Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of an Intereſt in Him; grounded on Gods <hi>free offer</hi> of Him to all Sorts of People; this is the Ground of comming to him, and entertaining of him, (for if this were not, People would never receive Him) this ſeemes to be no more then a confide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in his ability &amp; willingnes <hi>to ſave all that come unto Him,</hi> and in the truth of Him, gives record of Him:</p>
                  <p>The other is, a more Certaine Thing, grounded on the Knowledge of an <hi>Intereſt in Chriſt;</hi> Becauſe a Soule knowes it hath Chriſt for <hi>Its owne;</hi> Therefore it reſts on Him confidently for Salvation: This followes the Knowledge of our <hi>Beleeving,</hi> and is a farther act and degree of <hi>Faith,</hi> and comes <hi>after</hi> our Comming to Him and Receiving of Him. The former may not appeare,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113054:13"/> though it ever is, where <hi>Chriſt is beleeved on;</hi> and is weaker according as the the act of <hi>Faith</hi> is weaker; And that makes ſome Divines make <hi>Faith</hi> to be a reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on Gods Authority, or a truſt in the Truth of God that ſpeakes; for this ever is, where <hi>Faith</hi> is:</p>
                  <p>Thus, all Things conſidered, wee ſee, <hi>Faith,</hi> may be ſo defined, as I have done; Viz: <hi>The act of the whole Man &amp;c.</hi> It is an <hi>Entertayning Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Reſigning himſelfe to Chriſt;</hi> Therefore, it is called an <hi>acknowledging Chriſt,</hi> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 3. as it is in the Greeke <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. And therefore, expreſt by a Womans marrying a Man, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 4. which is an entertaining by covena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of a man, reſigning up hir ſelfe to him; And it is expreſt by <hi>Ingrafting, Rom.</hi> the 11. whereby the Science embraceth the Stock for its Roote &amp; Meanes of Life &amp; Fruite, and is given up to the Stock to be preſerved &amp; furniſhed with Sap, and made fruitefull by it.</p>
                  <p>Onely in this, there is this difference; The Fruite followes the Science &amp; Impe, and not the Stock: But the <hi>Beleevers Fruite</hi> is <hi>Chriſts,</hi> the <hi>Stocks,</hi> and not Its owne: And this ſeemes to be <hi>Paules beleeving;</hi> For, <hi>Acts.</hi> 9. 6. when he perceived that <hi>Ieſus was God in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> and ſo <hi>raiſed from the dead &amp;c.</hi> (as appeared by that Viſion &amp; Voice) then <hi>Paule,</hi> entertaines him, and reſignes up himſelfe to him, in thoſe Words: <hi>Lord what wilt thou have me to doe?</hi> as if he had ſaid <hi>Lord, ſave me,</hi> and <hi>rule thee, I become thine &amp;c.</hi> And this ſeemes to be <hi>Faith;</hi> for the <hi>Fruite</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> is found in him <hi>Verſ.</hi> 11, <hi>He prayeth</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Lord</hi> of him) and <hi>Verſe.</hi> 17. <hi>Ananias</hi> calls him <hi>Brother;</hi> and together with this ſight, he was to <hi>receive the Holy-Ghoſt,</hi> which was a ſigne of <hi>his beleev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> And in the 22. <hi>Chapter.</hi> where the Story is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated, <hi>Verſe.</hi> 16. <hi>Ananias</hi> haſtneth him to be <hi>baptized:</hi>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:113054:14"/> therefore, he tooke it for granted that <hi>He beleeved,</hi> or elſe he would have ſaid as Phillip <hi>Acts.</hi> 8. 37. to the Eunuch, <hi>If thou beleeveſt with all thy Heart, thou mayſt be baptized:</hi> And thus it is a Perticuler application of <hi>Christ,</hi> to a Mans ſelfe; for one cannot entertaine him and reſigne up ones ſelfe to him; but we doe perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letly apply him; as the marrying a Man, or ingrafting an Impe, is, a perticuler application of them: So there is a perticuler application of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that is not ever with the firſt act of <hi>Faith:</hi> and that is an <hi>aſſurance</hi> that <hi>Chriſt is mine</hi> (for this followes the reflect act; whereby I knowe that I beleeve) There is another, and that is a taking <hi>Chriſt</hi> for <hi>mine,</hi> and giving up <hi>my ſelfe</hi> to <hi>Him;</hi> and this is ever, where there is <hi>Faith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Againe, as it is an entertaining Chriſt, and reſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up ones ſelfe to him; So it is an entertaining and reſigning up to <hi>Him</hi> in all <hi>his Offices:</hi> whole Chriſt, not ſome part of Chriſt: Therefore, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1. 12. <hi>a receiving him,</hi> not ſome part of him, <hi>Pſal</hi> 2. 12. <hi>a kiſſing Chriſt.</hi> As the Woman in marriage takes the whole Man; as <hi>Exodus.</hi> 12. the <hi>whole Lambe</hi> was to be <hi>roaſted &amp; eaten.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is the difference twixt falce <hi>Faith</hi> &amp; <hi>true,</hi> And the reaſon of ſo many Peoples miſcarriage: They re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>receive &amp; apply Chriſt, in ſome one Office, as to be a Preiſt, But not in all his Offices, to be a King &amp; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet; whereas God hath joyned them alltogether, &amp; they cannot be parted: <hi>God</hi> conveyed Helpe to <hi>Iſraell,</hi> by all thoſe three Offices, Kings, Preiſts, &amp; Prophets. So doth he <hi>Salvation</hi> to Soules: Therefore, that <hi>Iſay.</hi> 33. 22. <hi>Chriſt</hi> muſt be entertained &amp; reſigned up to; As to our <hi>King,</hi> to be wholly ruled by his Lawes: As to our <hi>Prophet,</hi> to be onely taught by his Directions; Aſwell as to our <hi>Preiſt,</hi> to be onely reconciled to God,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113054:14"/> and inabled for performance with acceptance in all Services, <hi>by Him:</hi> This was it that he wanted, who is ſaid to want the <hi>wedding garment:</hi> Indeed, none can be actually, &amp; perfectly ſubject <hi>to Him</hi> as <hi>King</hi> &amp; <hi>Prophet,</hi> but this muſt they be willing, &amp; covenant, &amp; indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor to doe; and ſo to expect Salvation <hi>by Chriſt</hi> through his execution of all thoſe <hi>Offices;</hi> when he ſhall be <hi>in us</hi> aſwell as <hi>for us,</hi> a <hi>King, Preiſt, &amp; Prophet:</hi> This is to <hi>Beleeve.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now the Ground of thus doing, and ſo of <hi>Faith,</hi> is <hi>Gods free offer of Chriſt,</hi> on theſe Tearmes, thus to be had, with his promiſe of Salvation <hi>by Him</hi> to all that ſo <hi>entertaine Him;</hi> therefore, the doing this, is called the <hi>ſetting to a Seale</hi> that <hi>God is true;</hi> and the not doing it, is called the <hi>Making God a lyer</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="reasons">
                  <head>THE REASONS of this DOCTRINE. <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſons of the Doct.</note>
                  </head>
                  <p>Why thus to doe, as hath been explained, is, <hi>All that God requires,</hi> and the <hi>onely Meanes of obtaining Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Salvation by Chriſt:</hi> Are.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, Becauſe <hi>Chriſt &amp; Salvation,</hi> are <hi>Gifts of God, Iohn.</hi> 4. 10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. <hi>laſt.</hi> (for in them <hi>God ſeekes the praiſes of his Grace; Eph</hi> 1. 6. and ſo they muſt be Gifts &amp; free Things) Now a Gift, muſt not be deſerved, for then it is a Debt, Nor, have any thing done for it, but the receiving it; for elſe, it is an Exchange, no Gift: And indeed this is one maine reaſon, why <hi>God</hi> ſo magnifies <hi>Faith,</hi> as to make it the <hi>onely Meanes</hi> of <hi>obtaining Christ &amp; Salvation;</hi> Becauſe <hi>Faith</hi> onely magnifies <hi>Gods free Grace;</hi> For if any thing were done; then <hi>Chriſt &amp; Heaven</hi> could not be <hi>Gifts;</hi> And this alſo ſhewes that <hi>Faith onely</hi> as it is a <hi>receiving Chriſt</hi> (and no other way, not as it is an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, or Deed done) is the <hi>Meanes</hi> of obtaining
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113054:15"/> 
                     <hi>Chriſt &amp; Salvation by him:</hi> Becauſe elſe, they could not be <hi>Gifts,</hi> nor of <hi>Grace, Rom.</hi> 4. 16. <hi>Therefore it is of Faith, that it might be by Grace.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, Becauſe <hi>Man</hi> ſhould be <hi>abaſed,</hi> and ſtript of <hi>all boaſting;</hi> for whilſt that nothing is required of him for having Chriſt &amp; Salvation, but receiving and taking it, he can attribute <hi>nothing</hi> to himſelfe; <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 27. <hi>Where is Boaſting then? It is excluded, by what Law: of Workes? nay: but by the Law of Faith</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, Becauſe this makes <hi>Salvation ſure to us; Rom.</hi> 4. 16. <hi>It is of Faith, to the end the Promiſe might be ſure;</hi> for that it is grounded on <hi>God</hi> his <hi>Truth &amp; Faithfullnes,</hi> and not on us, as it was in <hi>Adam.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There are two Things by which ſome abuſe this <hi>Doctrine;</hi> which muſt be removed.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Some be ready to thinke; If all that God requires to Salvation be the <hi>Beleeving in Chriſt,</hi> then may we live in Sinne as we liſt; and yet come to Chriſt, beleeve in Him, and ſo be ſaved.</p>
                  <p>I Anſwer, but this is prevented by the deſcription of <hi>Comming to Chriſt, receiving of Him,</hi> or <hi>beleeving on Him;</hi> It is (as ye heard) the entertaining and reſigning up one ſelfe to Chriſt <hi>in all things,</hi> to be taught &amp; ruled by him, aſwell as to be ſaved by him; and they that doe not this; doe not come to Chriſt, nor receive, nor beleeve in him; So that the very nature of <hi>Beleeving,</hi> and a carnall Heart, &amp; Life, are incompactible. Faith <hi>unites</hi> to Chriſt, and ſo from Chriſt there is communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, <hi>Death to Sinne, Reſurrection to newnes of Life.</hi> Faith <hi>affords</hi> many holy reaſonings, whereby the Heart is ſtirred againſt Sinne, and to Obedience, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 10. 11. <hi>Likewiſe reckon ye alſo your Selves to be dead indeed unto Sinne, but alive unto God through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:113054:15"/> 1. <hi>Peter.</hi> 4. 1. <hi>For as much the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as Chriſt hath ſuffered for us in the flesh, arme your ſelves likewiſe with the ſame mind &amp;c.</hi> They that <hi>beleeve,</hi> are married to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and therefore <hi>bring forth fruite</hi> by Him <hi>to God, Rom.</hi> 7. 4. Chriſt <hi>Lives in them that beleeve, Gall.</hi> 2. 20. And <hi>dwelles in their hearts, Eph.</hi> 3. 17. <hi>Faith works by Love, Gall.</hi> 5. 6. And <hi>Love makes us keepe</hi> (that is, Evangelically; in deſire &amp; indeavor) <hi>all the Commands.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Some be ready to thinke; If all that be required to gett Chriſt &amp; Salvation, be to <hi>come to Chriſt, receive &amp; beleeve in Him,</hi> then it is not ſo hard a worke to be ſav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as it is made to be, for that it is an eaſy &amp; ſhort worke, to doe this.</p>
                  <p>I Anſwer but this is a groſſe miſtake, for that there is nothing in the World harder then to Come to, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, or Beleeve <hi>in Chriſt;</hi> therefore <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith; <hi>No Man can come to me except the Father draw him Ioh.</hi> 6. 44. he muſt be drawne, and that by an Allmighty Hand; or he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not come: Therefore when ſo many were invited, <hi>None came, Luke the.</hi> 14. they all made <hi>excuſe;</hi> and they that came, <hi>were compelled, Verſe.</hi> 23. and therefore the <hi>Perfecting of Faith</hi> is attributed to <hi>Power,</hi> 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1. 11. and the <hi>Diſciples</hi> pray for the <hi>Increaſe of Faith:</hi> There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that conduceth to <hi>Beleeving,</hi> but it is all aboue the Power of Nature, and contrary to Mans inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; As to goe wholy out of ones ſelfe, and reſt on an other for all good; To apprehend Sinne &amp; its miſery; Therefore the <hi>Spirit</hi> muſt come from Heaven to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of Sinne, Iohn.</hi> 16 8. And then to apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d a way of being <hi>Iuſtified from Sinne;</hi> the <hi>Spirit</hi> muſt likewiſe come from Heaven to <hi>Convince of Righteouſnes:</hi> which needed not, if any thing but <hi>God</hi> could doe it; And ſo for a Man to renounce his <hi>owne will &amp; wayes,</hi> and give
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113054:16"/> up himſelfe to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> whoſe <hi>Lawes</hi> be ſo contrary to Mans will; this is above Nature: Alſo the Devill is moſt ſtrongly againſt this; hence ſo many diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements &amp; ſubtill tentations are put on them that indeavor to <hi>beleeve;</hi> for Satan knowes that this onely gives <hi>Chriſt</hi> the <hi>Kingdome</hi> and turnes him out. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, therefore is it ſo hard to be ſaved, and ſo few are ſaved; becauſe it is ſo hard to <hi>beleeve,</hi> and ſo <hi>few</hi> doe <hi>beleeve.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But it is farther objected againſt this <hi>Doctrine;</hi> thus, The <hi>Scripture</hi> calls for many Things beſides <hi>Faith</hi> of them that be ſaved; as legall Humiliation, Mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, Holynes, Obedience &amp;c. Therefore it ſeemes that <hi>Beleeving</hi> or <hi>Comming to Chriſt</hi> is not all that <hi>God</hi> requires.</p>
                  <p>I Anſwer, The Legall Humiliations, and all wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Spirit, with the ſight of Sinne, are required, not as Meanes by which we pertake of <hi>Chriſt &amp; Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> (for many have them that never obtaine Chriſt or Salvation) but as <hi>Preparations</hi> whereby People are fitted, &amp; inclined, and drawne, to Come to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to Receive, &amp; Beleeve <hi>on Him;</hi> and they be one Meanes by which the Father drawes and the Miniſters com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell People to come; And <hi>Mortification, Holynes, Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence &amp;c,</hi> are onely the <hi>Fruites &amp; Effects</hi> of our <hi>Beleeving;</hi> that, which <hi>Chriſt</hi> doth in them, he meanes to ſave, after they have <hi>beleeved in Him;</hi> Theſe are the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginings of Salvation &amp; Glory which Chriſt begines and perfects in them that come to Him for Salvation; So that allthough theſe muſt be in all that be ſaved; Yet there is no other Meanes required of God for Obtaining Chriſt and Salvation, but onely Beleev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="1" type="application">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:113054:16"/>
                  <head>USES.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> Firſt <hi>Vſe,</hi> may ſerve for <hi>Inſtruction,</hi> in Three Perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culers. <note place="margin">Inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. To ſhew us in the Generall what to obſerve in <hi>Mans Salvation,</hi> Viz: <hi>Free Grace, Certainty,</hi> and that <hi>God</hi> is <hi>All in All,</hi> in <hi>Itt;</hi> Theſe (as ye heard in the Reaſons of the Point) are manifeſted aboundantly in <hi>Gods</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring no other <hi>Meanes</hi> of getting <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but <hi>onely Beleeving:</hi> Therefore let us ſee theſe in God his ſaving of People; This is indeed the ſweetnes of the Goſpel, and that which makes it ſo much glorifie God &amp; incourage miſerable Man; that it aſſures us, all Happynes is to be had in Chriſt, for receiving it.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. To ſhew their <hi>Error,</hi> that labour moſt for Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, Wealth, Honour, Content &amp;c. Whereas theſe neither are <hi>Meanes,</hi> nor are <hi>required by God,</hi> for our getting <hi>Christ &amp; Salvation:</hi> Therefore folly <hi>it is</hi> to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for them more, then to <hi>Beleeve.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. To ſhew the <hi>Errors,</hi> both, Of Papiſts, who ſeeke Salvation by Workes alſo, and not by <hi>Faith onely;</hi> and ſo make it neither <hi>Free Grace &amp; Gift,</hi> nor <hi>ſure;</hi> nor ſhutt Man out <hi>from all beaſting.</hi> And alſo, the <hi>Error</hi> of many among us (even that have ſome good thing in them) who, to the end they may get <hi>Chriſt &amp; Salvation,</hi> la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour moſt for Humiliation, or for Holynes, and leaſt of all, to <hi>Come to Chriſt, &amp; beleeve on Him;</hi> wheras <hi>onely Faith</hi> is the <hi>Meanes,</hi> and <hi>All</hi> that God requires for our <hi>obtaining Chriſt &amp; Salvation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There are <hi>Two Snares,</hi> which the <hi>Devill</hi> ſets for People.</p>
                  <p>One is, when they hope to be ſaved by Chriſt, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113054:17"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:113054:17"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:113054:18"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:113054:18"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:113054:19"/> 
                     <hi>never</hi> looke to be <hi>humbled,</hi> nor to be <hi>ſanctified;</hi> (thus the Profane are caught) which is a moſt ſilly thing, to thinke that any can be Saved, that be not regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated &amp; ſanctified; or to thinke that one can beleeve, &amp; not hate all Sinne, &amp; ſtudy all Holynes, or that any one can be brought to Heaven by Chriſt, and not to Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes firſt; It was a good ſpeech of <hi>Francis Spira,</hi> lying in the diſtreſſe of Spirit; <hi>I will not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>detract from the Goſpel,</hi> it is moſt true, that <hi>by Faith in Chriſt,</hi> we be <hi>onely ſaved,</hi> but yet, take heede of reſting on <hi>Faith,</hi> and neglecting the <hi>Workes of Faith,</hi> Faith requires not that we be Chriſtians in word onely; <hi>Beleeve me</hi> (qouth he) <hi>who have fully tryed the matter;</hi> and therefore he much commended to them, the <hi>Epiſtles of Peter,</hi> which preſſe <hi>Sanctity &amp; Chaſtity &amp;c.</hi> This was good Counſell, and very uſefull againſt this Snare, by which Satan intangles the moſt of People, who reſt in a Conceite that they beleeve, and never care for the <hi>Workes of Faith;</hi> but the Error of this hath been opened before.</p>
                  <p>There is an other <hi>Error,</hi> which is a <hi>ſecond Snare</hi> of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan;</hi> Viz: To labour for Humiliation, Mortification, Holynes &amp; Obedience, and <hi>not to labour to Beleeve;</hi> this is the <hi>Snare</hi> in which many well diſpoſed People are caught: And the <hi>Error</hi> of it appeares by this <hi>Doctrine;</hi> Becauſe there is no other <hi>Meanes required by God</hi> for our <hi>obtaining Chriſt &amp; Salvation,</hi> but <hi>onely Faith:</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſome meaſure of Humiliation muſt be had, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we can <hi>beleeve</hi> (as ye have heard before) Viz: So much as may make one <hi>hunger after Chriſt,</hi> and be <hi>willing to receive Him</hi> on <hi>any Conditions;</hi> But when thus much is obtayned; (which is, when there is a ſerious labour after Mortification, and all Obedience) Yet then to labour for more Humiliation, or Holynes, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113054:19"/> not firſt &amp; cheifly to labour to beleeve in Chriſt; this is a great error; for there is noe other meanes to get Chriſt &amp; Salvation but Faith; So that all the other Labour is in vaine, and for that, which never can bring Chriſt or Salvation; (as if a Man that deſires to bring his dead Freind to Life, ſhould onely labour to bring him to the acts of Life (as to ſpeake walke &amp;c.) and not to the onely Meanes of Life: to have his Soule joyned againe to his Body) and that Satan knowes, and therefore putts them on it, to make them ſpend time &amp; paynes to noe purpoſe; To ſuch therefore, I may ſay, as <hi>Elisha</hi> in an other caſe, to the <hi>Syrians;</hi> 2. <hi>Kings.</hi> 6 19. <hi>This is not the Way;</hi> Ye ſeeke Salvation and Chriſt, but by farther meaſure of Humiliation, (hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing enough allready to make you willing) or by Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, you can not get them; there is but <hi>one Way, one Thing</hi> that <hi>God requires,</hi> and that is, <hi>to Beleeve;</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaid to <hi>Martha</hi> in an other caſe; <hi>Luke.</hi> 10. 41. 42. <hi>Ye are carefull about many things, but one thing is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary</hi> Viz: to Come to Chriſt, and Beleeve in him; to Entertaine him, and Give up your Selves to Him in all his Offices; doe this and you ſhall <hi>be ſaved;</hi> When this is done, then ſhall ye be able to attaine Mortification and Victory over your Luſts Sanctification &amp; Ability to Duty, and not before, Theſe be the Fruites &amp; Effects of Beleeving; and you muſt <hi>Beleeve,</hi> before you can have theſe; As the Woman muſt be marryed to the Man, before ſhee can have lawfull Children by him; And the Science muſt be ingrafted into the Tree, before it can beare Fruite: Were it not a ſimple thing, for a Woman to expect Children <hi>Legitimate</hi> by a Man and then ſhee would marry him; Or to expect that a Science ſhould firſt beare Fruite by the Sap of a
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:113054:20"/> Stock, and then ye would ingraft it to it; Or to expect that a Roome ſhould be firſt inlightned, and warmed in the cold Winter, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye would bring in a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle &amp; Fire; As abſurd is it, to expect <hi>firſt to be Sanctified</hi> and then to <hi>Beleeve in Chriſt;</hi> For <hi>Faith in Chriſt,</hi> is the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> of all Mortification &amp; Holynes; It is <hi>Chriſt</hi> that <hi>ſanctifies People, Heb.</hi> 2. 11. And of <hi>His Grace conveyes to us, Iohn.</hi> 1. 16. and he never doth it, but by <hi>our Faith in Him;</hi> (for it is by <hi>Faith</hi> that <hi>He lives in us &amp; dwells in us,</hi> as ye have heard) Holynes is the Meanes by which Chriſt after he is beleeved in, brings them that beleeve in Him, to Salvation:</p>
                  <p>It is therefore, a moſt prepoſterous, and wholy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable way, for People to labour for Holynes, or Heaven, or Chriſt; and not <hi>firſt &amp; cheifly</hi> to labor to <hi>Beleeve in Chriſt;</hi> The <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>onely Way is:</hi> being ſoe farr humbled, (as I ſaid before) as to <hi>hunger after Chriſt,</hi> and be willing to have him on any Tearmes, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>to labour</hi> to <hi>Beleeve,</hi> and after that is done, to labour for <hi>Mortificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> &amp; <hi>Holynes, By,</hi> &amp; <hi>From Chriſt</hi> to get it, <hi>Whome</hi> thou haſt made <hi>Thine owne</hi> by <hi>Faith:</hi> Wherefore, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you <hi>ſee your Error,</hi> who will not beleeve, till firſt you have the Spirit quickning you, Grace ſtrengthing you to Duty, and ſubduing Sinne in you, if you could thus find it in you, then you could beleeve and not elſe; This is the inverting Gods Order, and a way, that will never bring you to Chriſt, or Heaven.</p>
                  <p>Indeed (and I pray obſerve it) there is an Act of Faith; which cannot be had till this be had, and that Divines calls a reflect Act; where by a Soule beleeves that it doth beleeve: Before this can be, there muſt be Repentance, Holynes &amp;c. This is a knowing that we have <hi>Faith;</hi> this is not the neceſſary Meanes to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:113054:20"/> Salvation but to <hi>Aſſurance &amp; Comfort;</hi> But there is an other <hi>Act of Faith,</hi> Viz. the <hi>direct Act;</hi> which is <hi>Beleev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> not a Beleeving that I doe Beleeve; but a <hi>Beleeving,</hi> and this muſt be, before we can repent, or have, or doe any good; this is the <hi>Meanes</hi> and <hi>onely Meanes to be ſaved.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now conſider the abſurdity of <hi>your Error;</hi> before you labor to Beleeve, you labor to <hi>knowe</hi> you doe Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve; you will be <hi>ſure</hi> you doe Beleeve, before you will Beleeve, you labor for the <hi>Evidence of Faith,</hi> before you labor to have <hi>Faith it Selfe;</hi> you more and firſt, care for the Meanes of Aſſurance &amp; Comfort, of your Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, then the <hi>Meanes of being Saved;</hi> And one maine Ground of your doing thus, is partly <hi>Pride,</hi> that ye will not have all grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of <hi>Hope &amp; Mercy</hi> to be <hi>in God,</hi> and none in your Selfe; For obſerve it, you will not goe that way, which makes you ground your Salvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>onely on Chriſt,</hi> and not at all in your Selfe, but you muſt ſee ſomewhat in your Selfe, before you <hi>will beleeve;</hi> And partly it is not daring to <hi>venter</hi> your Soules on Gods bare Word, but you muſt ſee ſomewhat done by him in you, before you will credit him; For though He ſaith, that <hi>Whoever comes to Chriſt, and beleeves in Him, ſhall be Saved &amp; Sanctified;</hi> yet you will <hi>not beleeve,</hi> till you find he hath ſanctified you; and ſo dare not truſt his Word; and therefore it is that the <hi>Scripture</hi> makes every <hi>Vnbeleever,</hi> to make <hi>God a Lyar;</hi> Conſider that <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 5. 10</note> of <hi>Thomas Iohn.</hi> 20. 25. <hi>The Diſciples ſaid we have ſeene the Lord; But he ſaid, except I ſhall ſee the print of the nayles, and put in my fingers I will not beleeve;</hi> then <hi>Verſe.</hi> 29. <hi>Ieſus ſaid becauſe thou haſt ſeene me thou haſt beleeved, bleſſed are they that have not ſeene me and yet have beleeved.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Yea farther: By this meanes: you hinder the ſhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:113054:21"/> forth of <hi>Gods free Grace;</hi> For whilſt that you will <hi>not Firſt beleeve;</hi> but <hi>firſt</hi> will be able to doe ſomewhat, you make not <hi>Chriſt &amp; Heaven</hi> a <hi>free Gift;</hi> nor can it be <hi>free Grace</hi> in <hi>God;</hi> and ſo not ſeeing <hi>Gods free Grace,</hi> ye doe not ſo magnifie <hi>Him</hi> as elſe you would; nor find ſuch ſweetenes in the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> nor be ſo incouraged as ye might be; but ſinke, perplexe, &amp; wound your Soules by feares &amp; diſcourageme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, which indeede be grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, Alſo, you hinder your owne Certainty &amp; Aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce; For whilſt you ground <hi>your Beleeving</hi> on ſomewhat in your Selfe, and not onely on <hi>Gods free Promiſe &amp; Word of Truth:</hi> It being grounded, (partly at the leaſt) on your Selfe who change; it is uncertaine &amp; cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geable. By all this I beſeech you <hi>ſee your Error,</hi> who being ſo much humbled as is requiſite; labour for Humiliation, Holynes &amp;c. and doe not <hi>firſt &amp; cheifly</hi> labour to <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Objection. </seg>
                     </label> It may be <hi>Objected</hi> by ſome; But I have indeavored this <hi>Way</hi> as you teach, and <hi>have beleeved,</hi> and yet I find not <hi>Chriſt &amp; Holynes</hi> follow after.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>1</label> I Anſwer, Firſt it is not poſſible <hi>to Beleeve,</hi> in the leaſt meaſure or degree, but <hi>Christ &amp; Salvation</hi> muſt be had, becauſe <hi>God hath abſolutely promiſed it to Beleeving.</hi> And the <hi>Spirit &amp; Sanctification</hi> muſt be had, for theſe be as inſeperable as Light from the Sunne; but theſe things be not ever ſenſible to them that <hi>Beleeve.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. Becauſe, they doe not knowe &amp; conſider the firſt, leaſt &amp; weakeſt workes of Chriſt, in the beleeving Soule, but onely judge themſelves by the more full &amp; ſtrong workings of Chriſt in the Soule; In trying the truth of Faith, take the weakeſt Evidences ſo they be ſure, (though reſt not there, for that, true Grace will never doe) as if a Man judgeth Life, onely by walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:113054:21"/> &amp; eating, he may thinke a Man that ſleepes is dead.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Becauſe the Act of Faith is not ſtrong enough to put forth it Selfe very ſenſibly, as the Acts of the Soule in a Swound; inaſmuch as there is not a freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t accuſtomed acting and exerciſing Faith, till by pract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſe the Heart is ſetled in it.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Becauſe there is not a reflect Act, a Conſidering what it is to Beleeve, and that thou haſt ſo done, and then a drawing the comfortable Concluſions to thy Selfe that flowe thence; and from Faith, a reaſoning to quicken thee up; for <hi>Faith</hi> produceth its Effects <hi>by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> As thus, <hi>If Christ hath ſuffered in the flesh,</hi> then muſt I <hi>make the flesh ſuffer in me; If Chriſt roſe againe,</hi> then <hi>muſt I riſe to newnes of Life.</hi> If <hi>Chriſt loved me ſo as to give Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for me.</hi> Then ſhall not <hi>I love Him ſo as to give my Luſts for Him &amp;c.</hi> Let theſe Things be obſerved, and there is none that doe in the leaſt meaſure <hi>truly Beleeve,</hi> But they ſhall find <hi>Chriſt &amp; Salvation</hi> made theirs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly I Anſwer; If thou haſt indeavored to <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve,</hi> and yet obtaineſt not <hi>Chriſt;</hi> It is not, becauſe this is <hi>not</hi> the way, &amp; the <hi>onely Way &amp; Meanes to get Him;</hi> But becauſe thou haſt <hi>not Beleeved,</hi> thou haſt not gon this <hi>Way,</hi> nor uſed this <hi>Meanes rightly:</hi> Therefore thou muſt not give over this <hi>Way,</hi> but labour to find it out, If there be many Pathes in a Feild and but one that leades to the Houſe a Man is going to, and he have gon to the end of one Path, and finds not the Houſe, It is a good reaſon why he ſhould thinke that is not the right Path, and ſo ſeeke it out, but no reaſon why he ſhould leave that Feild and betake himſelfe to a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>other for in that Feild onely is the Path; So it is no reaſon that thou ſhouldſt ceaſe ſtriving to <hi>Beleeve,</hi> and take to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:113054:22"/> ſome other Courſe; but labour to find out what it is to <hi>Beleeve,</hi> and then care to doe that.</p>
                  <p>And as this <hi>Doctrine</hi> ſhewes their <hi>Error</hi> who labour to Repent, to be Holy &amp;c. and not <hi>firſt to Beleeve.</hi> So it alſo ſhewes their <hi>Error;</hi> who finding a decay in their Soules of <hi>Grace;</hi> and an increaſe of <hi>Sinne;</hi> ceaſe their <hi>Faith,</hi> and lay it aſide and take to ſome other Courſe: Whereas, the onely way &amp; meanes for them to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver themſelves, is to recover, ſtrengthen &amp; increaſe their <hi>Faith,</hi> for <hi>Faith</hi> is the <hi>onely Meanes</hi> to <hi>Chriſt &amp; Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="application">
                  <head>2. USE. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> 
                  </head>
                  <p>For <hi>Exhortation,</hi> To exhort ye all to labour above all things, <hi>to Beleeve;</hi> that is, <hi>To entertaine Chriſt,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne up your Selves to <hi>Chriſt</hi> in all his <hi>Offices</hi> to be ſaved through them: Mind this Worke moſt of all, for it is the <hi>all in all</hi> to your Salvation; Thus did <hi>Paul Phill.</hi> 3. 8. 9. <hi>Yea doubtles I count all things but loſſe for the excelency of the knowledg of Chriſt; and doe count all but Dunge that I may winne Chriſt; And be found in him, not having mine owne Righteouſnes, which is of the Law, but that which is through the Faith of Chriſt:</hi> This is a worke I commend to you, and Command you in <hi>Gods Name:</hi> It is <hi>Gods Worke</hi> that which he moſt chargeth on you under the <hi>Goſpel, Iohn.</hi> 6. 29. doe yee make it your cheife worke:</p>
                  <p>You that take up your Thoughts &amp; Hearts moſt with the World, with the Honours, Pleaſures, or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits thereof; I might exhort you to beleeve (for till you doe it you cannot be ſaved) but you are to farr off from <hi>Faith</hi> yet; You are to be exhorted to get <hi>Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations</hi> for <hi>Faith;</hi> your Hearts to be ſo affected by the Law, with a ſight of your Sinnes, and Miſery by it,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:113054:22"/> that ye may be brought to <hi>thirſt after Chriſt,</hi> and will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to entertaine him on any Conditions; Mind ye this above all, becauſe without this, ye cannot come to <hi>Faith, that onely brings Chriſt &amp; Salvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> This Worlds Honours, Pleaſures, &amp; Profits, cannot give you <hi>Chriſt</hi> nor <hi>Salvation,</hi> and why then ſhall they be prefered &amp; minded &amp; ſought after more then <hi>Faith,</hi> and that Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation which fits for <hi>Faith?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But I will not addreſſe my <hi>Exhortation</hi> to you; But to Such as be humbled &amp; troubled with their Sinnes, &amp; Cry out, <hi>What ſhall we doe to be ſaved?</hi> To you I ſay, as <hi>Luke.</hi> 8. 50. <hi>Feare not, onely Beleeve:</hi> Yee have but one thing to doe, there is but one thing God requires of you, and you ſhall have <hi>Chriſt &amp; Salvation:</hi> And that is <hi>to Beleeve:</hi> Oh doe it! this will certainly, bring you all you deſire: <hi>Acts.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>What muſt I doe to be ſaved, Ver.</hi> 31. <hi>And they ſaid beleeve on the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and thou ſhalt be ſaved;</hi> And although <hi>Peter</hi> preſt them to <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent,</hi> as <hi>Acts.</hi> 2. 38. Yet that is, but as if he had ſaid <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve,</hi> Which in &amp; by <hi>Repentance</hi> will ſhew forth it Selfe &amp; worke in you; If ye feare Hell &amp; deſire <hi>Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> then <hi>Beleeve.</hi> This is the one &amp; <hi>onely way,</hi> All other Things that be good, come after this; All other La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of thine, is in vaine till this be done; Therefore this is ſo called for, and preſt in <hi>Scripture;</hi> It is charged on People by a Command. 1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3. 23. <hi>This is his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement: that we ſhould beleeve on the Name of his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> And ſo is in that <hi>Call to Repent, Acts,</hi> 17. 30. for till they <hi>Beleeve,</hi> they cannot <hi>Repent;</hi> And it is required with the greateſt reward promiſed, &amp; threat annexed, <hi>Marke.</hi> 16. 16. <hi>He that beleeveth &amp; is baptized ſhall be ſaved, but he that beleeveth not ſhall be damned.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To perſwade you to this duty, Conſider the evill of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:113054:23"/> not Beleeving, And the <hi>Benifite of Beleeving.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Evill of not Beleeving is very great; Its very Injurious to God, Chriſt, and your Selves.</p>
                  <p>To God; It makes him a Lyer, whereas <hi>Beleeving,</hi> ſetts to your Seale <hi>that God is true;</hi> therefore it is called <hi>a Iuſtifying of God, Luke</hi> 7. 29. 30. <hi>His truth &amp; faithfullnes,</hi> And not Beleeving, is a condemning God, as not true &amp; faithfull; You alſo wrong God in not obeying his Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand (which is <hi>to Beleeve)</hi> and in not regarding his Feaſte: nor valueing his Dainties: which made him ſay they that did ſo <hi>ſhould not taſt of them;</hi> for he that beleeves not, is expreſt by them that refuſed to come when the Supper was prepared <hi>Luke,</hi> the 14 And ſo ye wrong him in not receiving his Sonne (for that is <hi>Beleeving)</hi> when he proffers &amp; ſends him to you.</p>
                  <p>It alſo is Injurious to Chriſt; Its a ſlighting him, as if he were not worth the taking, It is a refuſing to <hi>kiſſe Him,</hi> and to let him <hi>raigne</hi> over you, and a <hi>Hating Him, Luke.</hi> 19. 14. It is as much as to ſay he is not worth the taking up, he is not ſufficient, or not free to helpe.</p>
                  <p>It is alſo Injurious to your owne Soules, <hi>Luke.</hi> 7. 30. <hi>againſt themſelves</hi> (that is not beleeving they did wrong themſelves, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3. 19. It is <hi>The Conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation;</hi> many <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> ye have viz. <hi>Oathes, Lying &amp;c.</hi> but this is <hi>The Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation;</hi> Ye doe keepe your Selves <hi>fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Salvation,</hi> becauſe this is the <hi>onely Meanes,</hi> &amp; ye will not uſe it; Ye doe that, <hi>Acts,</hi> 13. 47. Judge your Selves <hi>unworthy,</hi> and make the Preachers of Chriſt be turned from you; And for you that by diſcouragme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts are kept fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>Beleeving,</hi> ye keepe your Soules, from that pertaking of Chriſt, and his Benifites which ye might attaine to; And ſo alſo, ſuch as doe beleeve but weakely, they wrong God, Chriſt, and themſelves very much; as if their food which God
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:113054:23"/> provides were not good enough; as if <hi>Christ</hi> the <hi>Second Adam</hi> were not as good to helpe them, as the <hi>Firſt Adam</hi> was to hurt them; and keepe themſelves from that meaſure of Grace from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which they might attaine to.</p>
                  <p>As the Evill of not Beleeving is great; So is the <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifite of Beleeving;</hi> Its as effectuall as doing was with <hi>Adam,</hi> With him it was, <hi>doe &amp; live;</hi> Now it is <hi>Beleeve and Live:</hi> Not that God loves a <hi>fruitles Faith,</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is <hi>Faith</hi> that muſt helpe to doe, and that is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eſteemed with <hi>God</hi> then doing, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 21. 22. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Faith</hi> brings <hi>Chriſts doing,</hi> which is <hi>Perfect,</hi> and Ours is not; <hi>Beleeving</hi> it is the very <hi>Key</hi> which opens <hi>Chriſt:</hi> in whom are <hi>unſearchable Riches,</hi> and gives <hi>enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance into Heaven:</hi> It is the <hi>Bucket</hi> by which we fetch <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> from that <hi>Well of Life;</hi> And all that have this <hi>Key &amp; Bucket,</hi> may take thence: And therefore it is, that many have <hi>noe Grace</hi> from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> becauſe they have <hi>no Faith in Chriſt:</hi> And others have ſo <hi>little Grace,</hi> becauſe they have ſo <hi>little Faith,</hi> for as we <hi>Beleeve,</hi> ſo is it unto us; <hi>Matb.</hi> 8. 13. It is the turning the <hi>Cock,</hi> which ſets all a flowing from <hi>God,</hi> both <hi>Mercy &amp; Grace;</hi> It is in the leaſt degree, a <hi>ſure Evidence of Heaven,</hi> gives <hi>Title</hi> to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and all <hi>Promiſes,</hi> brings <hi>Iuſtification, Sanctification, and Salvation,</hi> affords <hi>Adoption &amp; Sonnship, Iohn.</hi> 1. 12. Now then Conſidering the Evill of not Beleeving, and the <hi>Benifite of Faith,</hi> What canſt thou doe that is of ſo much Conſequence as to <hi>Beleeve.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To helpe thee to <hi>Beleeve:</hi> Obſerve theſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections. <note place="margin">Helpes to Beleeve.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt labour to underſtand &amp; be clearely convinced <note place="margin">1. Obſerve theſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections.</note> of theſe Perticulers.</p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:113054:24"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:113054:24"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:113054:25"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:113054:25"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:113054:26"/>
                  <p n="1">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. Chriſts <hi>Alſufficiency, to helpe thee</hi> to all things, need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to <hi>Salvation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Gods <hi>Offer, &amp; tender of Chriſt to all People,</hi> where the Goſpel comes, without reſpect, or limitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Perſons but <hi>onely</hi> of Conditions (which is the next Point to come in our Text.)</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. That God who offers him freely. <hi>Is moſt true &amp; able,</hi> and <hi>moſt ſincere &amp; willing to give.</hi> what he offers.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. That for the fitting us to have <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or before we doe ſeeke for him, God requires <hi>nothing,</hi> but ſo farr <hi>to ſee our Miſery,</hi> as to <hi>deſire Chriſt,</hi> and be <hi>willing</hi> to take <hi>Him</hi> on <hi>His owne Conditions,</hi> and that then we be fitteſt for <hi>obtaining Chriſt,</hi> when we ſee in our Selves nothing but <hi>emptines</hi> of all Good, and <hi>fullnes</hi> of Sinne &amp; Miſery.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 5. That <hi>Beleeving brings Chriſt &amp; all Grace,</hi> and muſt be the firſt thing we doe, to gett <hi>Chriſt or Grace.</hi> (which is the Point in hand)</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 6. That Chriſt <hi>readily imbraceth,</hi> and <hi>ſweetly incourag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all;</hi> that attempt, &amp; indeavour <hi>to beleeve in Him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 7. That the <hi>expreſſe Command</hi> of God, is upon <hi>All,</hi> where the Goſpel comes, <hi>That they do beleeve;</hi> Theſe are undoubted Truthes expreſſe in the Scripture, <note place="margin">2. Pract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ise theſe Things.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>Practiſe theſe Things.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. <hi>Pray</hi> to <hi>God</hi> for <hi>helpe &amp; grace to beleeve, for it is his gift.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Attend on the <hi>Preaching of the Goſpel, Faith comes by hearing Rom.</hi> 10. 17. </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. Strive <hi>to it,</hi> ſit not ſtill, give <hi>not way</hi> to Doubtings, and Tentations, and Carnall reaſonings, but reaſon from the above premiſed <hi>Propoſitions,</hi> and preſſe your owne Heart, with the <hi>Concluſions</hi> that muſt followe thence; Alſo ponder &amp; conſider of thoſe <hi>Propoſitions,</hi> &amp; reſiſt all that furthers Doubting, &amp; hinders Beleeving; Thus make it <hi>your worke &amp; trade,</hi> to <hi>worke your Heart to it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:113054:26"/>
                  <p n="4">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. Bring your Selfe <hi>To venture upon that which the Word ſets before you,</hi> even <hi>above</hi> Reaſon &amp; Hope, and without Sence; ſtudiouſly ſearch out, what it is <hi>to Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve,</hi> in the firſt &amp; leaſt act of it; and then doe that at a <hi>Venture,</hi> and commit your Soule to it, doing it, what ever riſeth againſt it in your owne reaſon: And thus <hi>Faith</hi> begines.</p>
                  <p>Thus much for the Second Thing in the Text: The <hi>Meanes</hi> by which this <hi>Bread of Life:</hi> The <hi>All ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Remedy of Mans miſery may be obtained.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <p>THE THIRD THING in the Text is the <note place="margin">The Third Thing in the Text.</note> PERSONS that may uſe this meanes, and ſo obtaine Chriſt: In thoſe Words: <hi>He that Commeth, He that Beleeveth.</hi> That is, <hi>Any One</hi> by <hi>theſe Meanes may obtaine Him;</hi> It is an indefinite Propoſition &amp; is equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent to a univerſall; It is as much as to ſay; <hi>Who ever Comes:</hi> (as it is elſe where put) <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3. 15. <hi>That Whoſoever beleeveth in Him, ſhould not perish, but have E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Life;</hi> upon the uſe of this Meanes, any Perſon whoever may obtaine Chriſt, &amp; Salvation by him.</p>
               <div type="doctrine">
                  <head>DOCTRINE. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                     </label> 
                  </head>
                  <q>CHRIST, and Salvation by CHRIST, are free for any PERSON whatſoever, to obtaine by Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving in CHRIST.</q>
                  <p>The meaning is not, onely, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is for all ſorts of People; for all Sorts of People ſhall actually have him, becauſe God hath Elect of all Sorts; both Men &amp; Women &amp; Children, Yonge &amp; Old, Poore &amp; Rich, Wiſe &amp; Foolish, One Nation &amp; Another &amp;c. But the meaning is this, that there is no perticuler Perſon in the World, which may not by <hi>Beleeving</hi>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:113054:27"/> have Chriſt, &amp; Salvation by him; Chriſt is ſo freely tendered to all Commers, to all Receivers, to all that Beleeve in him; that there is no perſon of any Sexe, Age, Country, Condition, or Sinnes whatever but <hi>by Beleeving</hi> may have <hi>Chriſt &amp; Salvation by Chriſt;</hi> This is expreſſe in the Text; whilſt our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſaith, <hi>He that comes, He that beleeves;</hi> that is, <hi>Whoever comes &amp; beleeves:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As it was in the type; the <hi>Braſen Serpent</hi> cured onely by being <hi>looked on,</hi> and it cured <hi>all</hi> that looked on it, ſo that whatever ſtung <hi>Iſraelite</hi> looked on it, by that meanes was cured; which tipyfied, that what Perſon ſoever, Came to Chriſt &amp; Beleeved on Him, ſhould be Saved; for allthough, the <hi>Serpent</hi> helped none (as it is like) but the <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> yet <hi>Chriſt</hi> is larger then that type, being for all whoever, one or other, that <hi>come to him;</hi> as <hi>Himſelfe applyes, &amp; expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds it Iohn.</hi> 3. 14. 15. &amp; in other <hi>Scriptures:</hi> And therefore, <hi>Marke.</hi> 16. 15. 16. He appoints <hi>His Diſciples to preach the Goſpel to every Creature,</hi> (that is to every one of Man-kind) and then adds, <hi>He that beleeves ſhall be ſaved;</hi> that is, whatever Creature of Man-kind, whoever among them doth <hi>Beleeve, ſhall be ſaved;</hi> Indeed where the Goſpel is not preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the People are not Commanded to Beleeve; and ſo the Obedience cannot be exacted from them, nor they punisht for the want of it; Yet the Commiſſion of Mercy, &amp; Pardon given out; is no way limited in regard of Perſons, but <hi>tenders Mercy &amp; Pardon without limitation of Perſons, upon Beleeving,</hi> and therefore where ever it comes, and is preached, it offers Chriſt &amp; Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>free</hi> for every Perſon of them <hi>whatever,</hi> to be <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by Beleeving;</hi> And it may be truly ſaid that Chriſt is <hi>free to be had,</hi> by any Perſon, <hi>by Beleeving;</hi> even as it was with the <hi>Iewes,</hi> in the Proclamation of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> 2.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:113054:27"/> 
                     <hi>Cron laſt, two laſt Verſes.</hi> and <hi>Ezrah.</hi> 1. 1. 2. 3. any Jew might have liberty &amp; freedome from Captivity, upon the tearmes of <hi>accepting it,</hi> for it was gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to all whoever, to depart that would depart. Now though it is true all did not take it, and ſo were not delivered, yet Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome was <hi>Free for every one,</hi> to be had by <hi>accepting it;</hi> So is it with <hi>Chriſt &amp; Salvation by Him;</hi> although not every one, nor the moſt doe obtaine it, becauſe they uſe not the <hi>Meanes,</hi> accept not the <hi>Tearmes</hi> &amp; <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And this was typified by the <hi>Yeares of Iubile</hi> (which typified <hi>Chriſt;</hi> as is cleare by <hi>Luke.</hi> 4. 19. <hi>Chriſt is to preach the acceptable Yeare;</hi> that is, the <hi>Iubil; He is to Preach it;</hi> that is, <hi>in &amp; by Him,</hi> it is performed &amp; declared) In thoſe <hi>Yeares</hi> any Servant of the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> might goe from his Maſter, and if he would goe, and ſo <hi>accept of Freedome,</hi> he was to <hi>have it, Deut.</hi> 15 12. 13. any <hi>Hebrew</hi> was to have <hi>Freedom</hi> in this <hi>Yeare,</hi> if he would <hi>accept it</hi> (though if he would not accept it, he was not to have it as we ſhall ſee heerafter) which taught, that <hi>any Perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> (for though the Tipe was limited, yet the <hi>Antitipe</hi> is not, becauſe the <hi>Wall of Seperation is removed)</hi> I ſay it taught, that <hi>any Perſon whoever,</hi> upon theſe <hi>Tearmes</hi> by theſe <hi>Meanes,</hi> Viz: <hi>Accepting Chriſt &amp; Salvation,</hi> that is, <hi>Beleeving in Him,</hi> ſhould have it: And this ſeemes to be implyed in <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 22. 23. That as there is <hi>no difference</hi> among People <hi>till they beleeve,</hi> (they are <hi>all Sinners)</hi> So there is <hi>no difference</hi> in <hi>Gods offer of Mercy in the Goſpel,</hi> Its on the ſame Tearmes; to be had <hi>a like by All;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> The <hi>Angels</hi> ſaid <hi>glad Tidings came to all People, Luke</hi> 2. 10. Now if <hi>Salvation</hi> might not be had by <hi>All,</hi> on the ſame Tearmes, then were it <hi>not glad Tidings to All,</hi> But this <hi>makes it glad Tydings to All;</hi> That <hi>All</hi> whoever, by Beleeving may have
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:113054:28"/> 
                     <hi>Salvation;</hi> therefore is that <hi>Luke.</hi> 2. 30. 31. <hi>Myne eyes have ſeene thy Salvation, which thou haſt prepared before the face of all People:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is another maine thing to be knowne; as, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the <hi>All &amp; onely Remedy;</hi> and that <hi>He is to be had</hi> by <hi>Beleeving;</hi> So that <hi>any Perſon whatever,</hi> by <hi>Beleev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> may <hi>have Him;</hi> As a Generall Pardon, offering Mercy to all Traytors which ſubmit &amp; come in; any Traytor whatever upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe Tearmes may have Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; Indeed <hi>Chriſt</hi> doth <hi>actually</hi> afford helpe to none, but to them that <hi>Beleeve,</hi> but his helpe is freely tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>all, upon their Beleeving,</hi> So that <hi>any One</hi> whatever <hi>Beleeving,</hi> ſhall have helpe by <hi>Chriſt;</hi> this is expreſſe, <hi>Revela</hi> 22. 17.</p>
                  <p>Neither let this Point be perverted, for it ſhewes not that any Perſon may have Chriſt &amp; Salvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, on a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tearmes (for ſo it ſhould juſtifie &amp; incourage carnall Libertines) Nor that all, or the moſt ſhall have Chriſt on theſe tearmes; that is, actually injoy him by thus doing, for the moſt ſhall not have <hi>Grace</hi> to doe ſo, though by ſo doing, they may have him; But the Point ſhewes, that any Perſon may have it, on <hi>Chriſts tearmes;</hi> and that every Perſon (where the Goſpel is preached) may &amp; ſhould indeavor to Beleeve, and <hi>Beleeving,</hi> ſhall <hi>have Chriſt;</hi> And this is moſt cleare, by thoſe <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> which expreſſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> by a <hi>Feaſt; Prov.</hi> 9. 1. <hi>Luke.</hi> 14. 16. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where <hi>all are invited,</hi> and upon <hi>comming</hi> might <hi>eate of the Feast;</hi> and the moſt unlikelieſt of all to be permitted to come, are inſtanced in; Viz: The <hi>Simple &amp; Fooles,</hi> the <hi>Poore,</hi> and the <hi>Hedge &amp; High way Perſons,</hi> to ſhew that <hi>None be excluded; out of the Offer,</hi> but on the ſame Tearmes any one whatever may come &amp; injoye <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="reasons">
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:113054:28"/>
                  <head>REASONS. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>
                     </label> 
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, Becauſe this much magnifies &amp; ſets out <hi>Gods Grace, &amp; Free-Mercy;</hi> whilſt that <hi>Chriſt &amp; Salvation,</hi> may not onely be had for taking; but alſo may be had by <hi>any One whatever, for taking.</hi> So freely to offer Chriſt and Salvation to a <hi>few</hi> were greate Mercy, but to <hi>offer it ſo freely to every one,</hi> that is <hi>Wonderfull Mercy;</hi> As it is great Mercy for a Prince, to offer Pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to one or two Traytors, upon the tearmes of accepting Pardon; but to tender it to all Traytors on the ſame free tearmes, is wonderfull Mercy; even as it was <hi>wonderfull Riches in Solomon</hi> in the 2. <hi>Cron.</hi> 1. 15, <hi>to make Silver at Ieruſalem as Stones;</hi> that is that any one whatever may have for tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up, if he deſires them (for ſo are Stones;) Even thus is the <hi>Riches of Gods Mercy,</hi> ſet forth: inaſmuch as <hi>Chriſt &amp; Salvation</hi> (Things of <hi>more worth</hi> then Gold &amp; Silver) are to be had by <hi>any whoever,</hi> if they accept the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that is, <hi>Beleeve in Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, Becauſe this <hi>Incourageth every one to obey the Goſpel, &amp; beleeve in Chriſt;</hi> inasmuch as <hi>Chriſt is not limited,</hi> nor are any ſequeſtred &amp; ſhut out from having Chriſt by Beleeving: Therefore there is good Incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement for any one, ſo for every one, to indeavor to Beleeve.</p>
                  <p>And this is a wiſe Adminiſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, for, by this meanes, they who live under the Goſpel, and yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve not, are left wholy without excuſe, even as that Man <hi>Math.</hi> 22. 12. <hi>ſpeechles;</hi> for it will be cleare (even their owne ſelves being Judges,) that they miſſed Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, becauſe they cared not for it, but loved other things better, for when it was free to be had by any one; by Receiving &amp; Beleeving, they would not doe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:113054:29"/> that; even as the Traytor, who receives not the free and generall Pardon, hath no plea nor excuſe left him, when he comes to receive the Sentence; And this ſeemes to be implyed in <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3. 19. The <hi>Condemnation</hi> to them that have heard the <hi>Goſpel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> will be this, <hi>That Light came into the World,</hi> (which muſt be ſupplyed) and might have been had by every one of them if they would have received it, but they would not ſo much as take it, when they might have had it, <hi>becauſe their deeds were evill;</hi> This free tender of Chriſt, It diſcovers the wickednes of their Hearts, the evill Deeds of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (for therefore they will not love, nor receive the light) and leaves them without all Plea, and makes their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to be of themſelves, their owne willfull ruine, who doe periſh under the Goſpel: And as there is this effect.</p>
                  <p>So alſo, by this meanes, the Perſons (as the <hi>Apoſtle ſpeakes</hi> 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 9.) <hi>are appointed by God to obtaine Salvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by Chriſt;</hi> they are brought on to Beleeve, and ſo to be ſaved by Chriſt; For God, doth not firſt, ſhew People that he hath Elected them, and then &amp; thereby per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade &amp; bring them to beleeve, but Election is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed as a ſecret thing, and by Gods offering Chriſt freely to every one to be had by Beleeving His free Offer incourageth them to labour to Beleeve, and they finding themſelves not ſhut out of Mercy, they labour to Beleeve, and God helpes &amp; gives them the <hi>Gift of Faith,</hi> and ſo they <hi>Beleeving,</hi> come to knowe that they are <hi>ordayned to Life Eternall, Acts.</hi> 13. 48. This is a wiſe courſe &amp; way to bring in the Elect, and diſcourage or hinder none. </p>
               </div>
               <div n="1" type="application">
                  <head>USE. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                     </label> 
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Incourag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> For <hi>ſpeciall Incouragement</hi> to every one of you <hi>To</hi>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:113054:29"/> 
                     <hi>come to Christ &amp; beleeve in Him;</hi> I now in Gods Name, as his Meſſenger &amp; Embaſſador; <hi>Tender &amp; Offer Chriſt to every One of You,</hi> on theſe <hi>Tearmes,</hi> that ye <hi>Come to Him, Receive Him, Beleeve in Him,</hi> and aſſure you, that ſo doing, <hi>Ye ſhall be ſaved by Him:</hi> I <hi>tender Chriſt to you All,</hi> onely annexing theſe Two Cautions leaſt ye ſhould miſtake or abuſe this <hi>Doctrine:</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Cautions.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, That none muſt meddle with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but they who <hi>be willing</hi> to have him on <hi>His owne Tearmes</hi> Viz. To be <hi>Lord &amp; King</hi> to them aſwell as <hi>Preiſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, Whoever <hi>doe get Chriſt,</hi> they are ſurely <hi>Changed by Him,</hi> and made <hi>New Creatures.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe being premiſed; I doe this Day, <hi>Offer Ieſus Chriſt to yee All,</hi> and <hi>aſſure yee</hi> He is to be had by you if ye Come to Him, Receive Him, Beleeve in Him; that is, <hi>If ye Entertaine Him,</hi> and <hi>give up your Selves to Him in all his Offices;</hi> upon theſe <hi>Tearmes,</hi> He may be had by any of you; It is moſt probable there be Some of You to whome God intends good; where He ſo freely ſends his Goſpel; Now let every one hope it is he. And indeavor to make it ſo; as men doe at a Dole: and let <hi>Heaven Suffer Violence.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Oh Receive Him then! Give up your Selves to Him in Covenant; Accept Him for your King, Preiſt, and Prophet; Reſolve this Day, The Lord Jeſus Chriſt, ſhall be my Prophet, I will in all Things la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to be Taught &amp; Guided by Him; And he ſhall be my King; I will in all Things care to be Ruled by his Lawes: And he ſhall be my Preiſt; I will reſt on Him for Attonement and Satisfaction to God-wards.</p>
                  <p>I muſt addreſſe my Selfe to Two Sorts of People among you.</p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:113054:30"/>
                  <p n="1"> 1. To ſuch of you as are <hi>Willing</hi> that Chriſt ſhould raigne over you, but dare not, or cannot truſt in Him <hi>for your Salvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>;</hi> be ye incouraged, for there is none ſuch but be <hi>wellcome to Chriſt,</hi> that is all he ſeekes, to raigne over you, it is all the tearmes he ſtands on, ye having granted him his owne Conditions, why ſhould ye queſtion his Mercy; This I ſay to you, 1. that if ye be made willing to give up your Selves to Chriſt in all things to be guided by him, and covet his Kingly Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice in your Soules, and ſtudy &amp; ſeeke for Holynes, And 2. If ye find, that hope of Mercy, makes ye feare to offend, &amp; care to pleaſe God in all things, and doth not make you preſumptuous, ſecure &amp; bold to Sinne; Then you may, and ſhould <hi>apply Chriſt for Mercy,</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect it from him; And doe it now, Now <hi>He is offered</hi> to you this Day, as a <hi>Preiſt to ſave you, &amp; reconcile God to you,</hi> accept it, in that <hi>Office</hi> &amp; put your truſt in him, Is he not <hi>free for every one</hi> upon theſe tearmes, and why will you neglect <hi>ſo free Mercy?</hi> You have ſinned againſt it hitherto, in doubting &amp; queſtioning of it, Oh now ſinne not any longer! but boldly venture thy ſelfe on Chriſt; feare not thy Wellcome, or being permitted to apply Chriſt, the <hi>free generall Pardon is given out;</hi> &amp; ſue it forth, whoever layes hold on Chrſt muſt be ſaved: <hi>Chriſt</hi> puts this out of doubt: <hi>Iohn.</hi> 6. 37. <hi>He that comes I will in noe wiſe ſend away;</hi> Limitt not, where God hath not limitted; doe not ſhut out thy Selfe, where God hath not ſhut thee out; doe not inquire whether thou art choſen or no, but looke to the Goſpel, in which Chriſt is freely tendered to every one on the tearmes of beleeving, and labour to beleeve; Therefore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all malitious ſuggeſtions of Satan, and againſt all carnall reaſonings of thine owne Heart, boldly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:113054:30"/> to rely on Chriſts Merrit for thy Juſtification and ſo doing thou ſhalt be ſaved; Thus reaſon with your Selfe; Doth God freely offer Chriſt to ſave all that entertaine him, and requireth nothing but our accepting him, why then ſhould not I venture my Soule on him, and reſt Confident? How can the God of Truth but be as good as his Word? And if he be ſo, how can I but obtaine Salvation by Chriſt, if I truſt in Chriſt? I would beleeve a Man whome I thought honeſt upon his word; and ſhall I not God, when I have his Word &amp; Oath?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. I am to ſpeake to another ſort of People; Viz: Such of you, <hi>as mind not Chriſt at all,</hi> or if you doe, yet not ſo much as to <hi>let him raigne over you,</hi> but are ſtill bent on your Luſts, &amp; your old &amp; former Wayes; Yee are they, who yet mind ſome thing in the World, to much, and are not willing to entertaine Chriſt for your <hi>King;</hi> Be ye now exhorted to receive him, and let him raigne over you; He may be had upon theſe Tearmes <hi>even by you</hi> (for he is free for every one on theſe tearmes) therefore entertaine him, let the World &amp; your Luſts goe, and <hi>chooſe Chriſt;</hi> Reaſon thus with your Selves; <hi>Is not the Love of the World enmity to God,</hi> ſo that <hi>He that is a friend to the World, muſt be Gods Enemy?</hi> The Things of the World they are but periſhing, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine, inſufficient Helpers, &amp; Comforters; And as for my Luſtes &amp; Wayes, are they not deceitfull, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing, &amp; damnable? Is not the <hi>Fruite of every Sinne, Shame;</hi> and the <hi>Wages Death?</hi> muſt I not leave them, &amp; get Pardon for them, or goe to Hell? Why then ſhall I prefer the World &amp; Sinne <hi>before Chriſt?</hi> And (as the Jewes in an other caſe) chooſe Barrabas a Murderer, and <hi>let Chriſt goe?</hi> At the Day of Judgment I ſhall <hi>need</hi>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:113054:31"/> 
                     <hi>Chriſt;</hi> But how can I thinke, <hi>Chriſt</hi> will owne me <hi>heerafter,</hi> if I <hi>now</hi> will not owne him, and let him rule over me? Will he not <hi>one Day,</hi> bid me depart, and ſay <hi>He knowes me not,</hi> if I be a <hi>Worker of Iniquity?</hi> Wherefore ſince <hi>Chriſt is ſo free,</hi> that I may receive him as well as any other, ſo that I will but renounce all my ſinnfull wayes, and give up my Selfe to Him; I will ſo doe: Whats the World &amp; my Luſts to <hi>Heaven &amp; Chriſt;</hi> which thus I may have?</p>
                  <p>Oh! that ye would be perſwaded this Day, to <hi>aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> the World &amp; your Sinnes, and <hi>Entertaine Chriſt for your Lord &amp; King;</hi> Doe it, when as you heare, that if you now accept Chriſt, ye ſhall be wellcomed; and though hitherto ye have been great Sinners; Yet now if ye <hi>abandon</hi> your Luſts, and <hi>embrace Christ;</hi> ye ſhall have him given, and all that is paſt freely forgiven: <hi>Oh! why will ye neglect ſo great Salvation?</hi> Doe not ſo, but doe this; <hi>Receive Chriſt;</hi> and now doe it; doe not defer the doing this, But now make this <hi>Covenant with Chriſt,</hi> even this Day, at this Time: Covenant in your Spirits with Chriſt; that you will accept Him in all his Offices to be yours, and give up your Selves to be his, and reſt on him for your Salvation; Now I ſay doe it, <hi>whilſt it is called too Day,</hi> and defer not; if now you will indeavor to doe it, Chriſt will helpe you forward; Incline to this happy worke, and the miniſtry of the Goſpel ſhall promove &amp; farther you; It is the <hi>Miniſtry of the Spirit,</hi> and not of the Letter; <hi>Gods Spirit</hi> accompanyes it, both to worke in you a <hi>Will</hi> to doe thus, and to <hi>Helpe</hi> them that are willing &amp; doe indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor it; But if ye ſhall defer Chriſt; and excuſe your not Comming, and put him off, ye can expect no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther returne but that, <hi>Luke.</hi> 14. 24. <hi>For I ſay unto you,</hi>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:113054:31"/> 
                     <hi>that none of thoſe men which were bidden ſhall taſt of my Supper:</hi> and ye may well feare, it ſhall fare with you, as with the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> who becauſe <hi>They would not accept Gods offer &amp; enter Canaan, when he tendred it,</hi> allthough a while after, they would have done it, and did indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor, yet God would never let them come into it: Where Gods Mercy is moſt free; he is uſually moſt quick &amp; ſevere; and they that may &amp; will not goe free, are ſerved, as the <hi>Servant that might,</hi> and would not. <hi>Deut.</hi> 15. 16. 17. No after Yeares of Jubile, could free them.</p>
                  <p>Remarkeable is the <hi>Speech of Francis Spira,</hi> (one of whome I told you before) when he languished un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the torture of his Conſcience, for preferring the World, before Chriſt: <hi>Oh ſaith he! that I could but hope in Gods Mercy; Oh! what would I give for one of thoſe ſweete Motions of Gods Spirit, to incline me, which I have had before &amp; ſlighted;</hi> A pittifull Caſe; and yet the like and worſe may yours be, if ye neglect or defer to take Chriſt, now that he is offered to you all; Therefore, if ye have any ſence or apprehenſion of Things Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, Eternall &amp; to Come, If ye have any feare of Hell, or deſire of Heaven; If any reſpect or reverence to God who thus condeſcends &amp; ſtoopes low, ſo as to <hi>Offer Chriſt &amp; Salvation to you,</hi> and <hi>Invite you to come &amp; take it;</hi> Be <hi>Exhorted to Come &amp; Beleeve in Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But if all this will not move you, then breifly Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what the <hi>Lord ſaith in his Word;</hi> where <hi>Chriſt is offered,</hi> and <hi>not received;</hi> Oh! how fearefull is that Peoples State?</p>
                  <p n="1">1. They are in a <hi>more Speciall</hi> deſperate ſubjection to <hi>Sinne</hi> then others; For <hi>Light is come into the World,</hi> and ſuch Men <hi>Loved Darkenes, rather then Light, becauſe their</hi>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:113054:32"/> 
                     <hi>deedes are evill; Iohn.</hi> 3. 19. Chriſt, <hi>Who is ſet for the riſing againe of many,</hi> is ſet alſo <hi>for the fall of others; Luke.</hi> 2. 34. 35. And <hi>for a ſigne which ſhall be ſpoken againſt, that the thoughts of many Hearts may be revealed;</hi> And heerein the <hi>Iniquity of Sinne</hi> is diſcovered.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. They <hi>muſt Perish;</hi> you heard before, how they that were <hi>Invited,</hi> and <hi>Came not,</hi> ſhould <hi>not taſt</hi> of the <hi>Supper,</hi> Therefore 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1. 7. 8. <hi>The Lord Ieſus ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed from Heaven, with his mighty Angells, in flaming Fire, to take Vengance;</hi> But on whome? <hi>On them that knowe not God,</hi> and <hi>Obey not the Goſpel of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> And the ſame <hi>Apoſtle</hi> tells us, <hi>If the Goſpel be hid, it is to them that perish</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 3. Such ſhall call for Chriſt &amp; Mercy, as <hi>Pro.</hi> 1. 24. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but ſhall be anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Him ye would not have;</hi> Such ſhall have in them as <hi>much feare of Chriſt,</hi> as of <hi>God,</hi> and as <hi>much danger from Chriſt,</hi> as from <hi>God;</hi> For <hi>Chriſt will be Wroth,</hi> and will certainely <hi>Have thoſe his Enemyes, which would not that he ſhould raigne over them, brought, &amp; ſlaine, before Him, Luke.</hi> 19. 27. Chriſt the <hi>Lambe,</hi> will be <hi>wroth,</hi> and ſuch ſhall be <hi>the day of his wrath, ſo great, &amp; terrible,</hi> as that <hi>men ſhall ſay, who ſhall be able to ſtand?</hi> &amp; therefore <hi>unbeleevers</hi> of all rankes, Kings, Great men of the Earth, Rich men, and the Cheife Captaines, Such as now dare looke Death in the Face, ſhall then <hi>Call to the Mountaines &amp; Rockes to fall on them, to cover them from that Wrath, Revel.</hi> 6. 15. 16. 17. And how can Such want ruine, When the <hi>Goſpel ſhall Iudge them;</hi> as Chriſt tells you it ſhall doe thoſe who heare it and doe not beleeve, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 12. 47. 48. <hi>The Word that I have ſpoken, the ſame ſhall Iudge them at the Laſt Day:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And Such ſhall not onely periſh, but <hi>Perish worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Others;</hi> The <hi>Goſpel is a Savour of Death unto Death to them,</hi>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:113054:32"/> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 15. 16. They are dead allready, but ſhall dye worſe; They are fallen in <hi>Adam,</hi> but ſhall fall far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Luke.</hi> 2. 34. Therefore that Place is very Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, <hi>Math.</hi> 10. 12. to. 16. <hi>And when ye come into an houſe, ſalute it. And if the houſe be worthy, let your peace come upon it, but if it be not worthy, let your peace returne to you. And whoſoever ſhall not receive you, nor heare your wordes: when ye depart out of that houſe or city, ſhake off the duſt of your feet. Verily I ſay unto you; It ſhall be more tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable for the land of Sodome &amp; Gomorrha in the day of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then for that Citie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus much for the third Thing in the Text; Viz: <hi>the Perſons</hi> that may uſe <hi>theſe Meanes,</hi> and ſo <hi>obtaine Chriſt:</hi> Now the Laſt followes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <p>THE FOURTH &amp; Laſt THING in the Text is <note place="margin">
                     <hi>The</hi> 4. <hi>Thing in the Text.</hi>
                  </note> the MOTIVE by which People are perſwaded to uſe this <hi>Meanes,</hi> and ſo get Chriſt, <hi>This Bread of Life,</hi> The <hi>Allſufficient Remedy of Mans Miſery:</hi> That is taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the great <hi>Benifite</hi> that by ſo doing, will redound to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: As appeares by theſe Wordes; <hi>Shall never Hunger, Shall never Thirſt;</hi> Whoever Comes to Chriſt, or Beleeves in Chriſt ſhall never Hunger nor Thirſt: As Bread alayes Hunger; So doth this <hi>Bread;</hi> This <hi>Christ;</hi> And that in a better manner then Bread doth; For, 1. Bread alayes Hunger &amp; not Thirſt; But <hi>Chriſt alayes Hunger &amp; Thirſt,</hi> more appetites then Bread doth. 2. Bread alayes but for a while, <hi>Chriſt alayes for ever;</hi> Paralell to this latter is that <hi>Iohn.</hi> 4. 13. 14. <hi>Whoſoever drinketh of this Water, ſhall thirſt againe: But whoſoever drinketh of the Water that I ſhall give him, ſhall never thirſt:</hi> Where the Compariſon is made, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> in this Reſpect, is prefered.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:113054:33"/>
               <p>For the underſtanding this; Yee muſt knowe, that although in ſome regard (as ye ſhall ſee heerafter) this may be taken Litterally, &amp; in ſome regard of the Body; that they that <hi>Beleeve in Chriſt, ſhall never hunger nor thirſt;</hi> Yet Cheifly this is to be taken <hi>Metaphorically,</hi> &amp; ſo largely, and ſo including the Litterall &amp; Corporall Sence, and the meaning is this:</p>
               <p>That all their Wants ſhall be <hi>ſupplyed,</hi> &amp; all Deſires <hi>alayed &amp; ſatisfied.</hi> But this is expreſt by not hunger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp; thirſting, becauſe of following the Metaphors of Bread &amp; Water, by which Chriſt is expreſt: Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering &amp; Thirſting, are painfull Deſires of ſome ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary good Thing thats wanting, the one of Meate, the other of Drinke, for the good of the Body; Now every Perſon having a reaſonable &amp; immortall Soule; hath many &amp; great Deſires, which be as ſo many Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerings &amp; Thirſtings; Now by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> all theſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires ſhall be alayed, by ſupplying all his Wants, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> is had <hi>by Beleeving:</hi> This is the <hi>Meaning:</hi> The <hi>Doctrine</hi> ariſing hence is.</p>
               <div type="doctrine">
                  <head>DOCTRINE. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                     </label> 
                  </head>
                  <q>Whoever Beleeves in CHRIST, ſhall have all his WANTS ſupplyed, and ſo, all his DESIRES alayed; and his SOVLE fully ſatisfied.</q>
                  <p>He ſhall be ſent away with a <hi>Compleate Satisfaction,</hi> as the hungry Man when he is filled with Meate, or the thirſty Man with Drinke.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Point</hi> is plaine &amp; expreſſe in the Text; If there were no other Proofes, we might build our <hi>Faith</hi> on it: But there are Divers</p>
                  <p>This was <hi>Propheſied off,</hi> under the ſame <hi>Metaphors; Iſay,</hi> 49. 9. 10. <hi>That thou maist ſay to the Priſoners, goe forth;</hi>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:113054:33"/> 
                     <hi>to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are in darknes ſhew your ſelves; they ſhall feede in the wayes, &amp; their paſtures ſhall be in all high places; they ſhall not hunger nor thirſt, neither ſhall the Heate nor Sunne ſmite the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for he that hath mercy on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhall lead them, even by the ſprings of Waters ſhall he guide them.</hi> To which Chriſt hath reference; <hi>Revel.</hi> 7. 16. 17. <hi>Tbey ſhall hunger no more, neither thirſt any more &amp;c.</hi> And is in expreſſe wordes promiſed, <hi>Ier.</hi> 31. 14. 25. <hi>And I will ſatiate the ſoules of the Preiſts with fatnes, and my people ſhall be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with goodnes, ſaith the Lord;</hi> And Verſe. 25. <hi>I have ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated the weary ſoule, &amp; I have replenished every ſorrowfull ſoule;</hi> And ſo <hi>Ier.</hi> 50, 19. <hi>I will bring Iſraell againe to his Habitation, and he ſhall feede on Carmel &amp; Bashan, and his ſoule ſhall be ſatisfied upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mount Ephraim &amp; Gilead.</hi> And therefore, it is affirmed, as made good by, &amp; in Chriſt; <hi>Luke.</hi> 1. 53. <hi>He hath filled the hungry wih good things;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. 8. 9. 10. The <hi>Beleever</hi> (who is after expreſt by the effects of Faith) <hi>fearing &amp; ſeeking God;</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> and why? becauſe <hi>He ſhall want no good;</hi> for that is <hi>Bleſſednes:</hi> Thus much is alſo inplyed in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55. 1. 2. 3. by Beleeving in Chriſt, (which is ment there by <hi>Comming Buying &amp;c.)</hi> they ſhall come to injoy all good things, that be requiſite to their wellfare, and ſo Conſequently ſhall have <hi>All deſires alayed:</hi> Therefore it is, that as all our <hi>Deſires</hi> are in the Text expreſt by <hi>Hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp; Thirſting,</hi> ſo <hi>Chriſt</hi> is expreſt by a Feaſt in Scripture and tipified by the Manna &amp; Rocke, that yeilded Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of Water in the Wildernes; to ſhew, that as by comming to a rich &amp; full Feaſt, there is a ſupply, of all the wants, &amp; an alaye, of all the deſires, of an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gry &amp; thirſty Man; So by <hi>Beleeving in Chriſt,</hi> all the <hi>Wants</hi> of People are <hi>ſupplyed,</hi> and all their <hi>Deſires alayed:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>Math.</hi> 5. 6. They which <hi>Hunger</hi> be <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> becauſe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:113054:34"/> they ſhall be <hi>Satisfied,</hi> If not <hi>Satisfied,</hi> they be not <hi>Bleſſed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="reasons">
                  <head>REASONS. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>
                     </label> 
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The <hi>Reaſon</hi> is grounded upon a two fold <hi>Propoſition.</hi> Firſt, That <hi>Beleeving poſſeſſeth a Man of Chriſt:</hi> He that Beleeves in Chriſt, hath, Chriſt, and <hi>is one with Chriſt;</hi> Therefore, (as ye heard before) <hi>Beleeving</hi> is compared to a Marrying, and to an Ingrafting <hi>into Chriſt:</hi> That looke as a Woman <hi>married</hi> to a Man, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyeth him as her owne; and a Science <hi>grafted,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyeth &amp; poſſeſſeth the Tree for its owne; So, <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever beleeveth in Chriſt:</hi> Injoyeth &amp; Poſſeſſeth Chriſt for their <hi>owne:</hi> Chriſt is the <hi>Gift of God Iohn</hi> 4. 12. and <hi>Faith</hi> is a <hi>receiving of this Gift Iohn.</hi> 1. 12. Now as a Man that hath received a gift doth poſſeſſe &amp; injoye it as his owne. So <hi>Beleevers</hi> receive Chriſt given of God, and ſo injoye &amp; poſſeſſe him as their owne, <hi>Faith</hi> makes us the <hi>Houſe of</hi> Chriſt; <hi>Chriſt dwells in the Heart by Faith, Eph.</hi> 3. 17. even as a man dwelleth in his Houſe, and ſo he hath Poſſeſſion of the Houſe; So <hi>have Beleevers of Chriſt:</hi> Hence when <hi>Thomas beleeved;</hi> he ſaith <hi>my Lord, my God;</hi> Therefore <hi>David Pſal</hi> 144. 1. 2. Challe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth <hi>God to be his,</hi> and why? <hi>He truſts in Him;</hi> in the end of the <hi>Verſe.</hi> So that <hi>Beleeving poſſeſſeth a Man of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly as Beleeving poſſeſſeth of Chriſt, &amp; maks him to be ours: So the <hi>Having Chriſt</hi> makes <hi>God to be ours;</hi> Chriſt brings to the <hi>Fruition &amp; enjoying of God;</hi> which may be gathered from his very <hi>Name;</hi> which is <hi>Emanuell,</hi> that is, <hi>God with us Math.</hi> 1. 23. which not onely implyes, that in him God is come in our Nature, becauſe <hi>he</hi> that <hi>is God</hi> tooke our Nature into Perſonall Union, but alſo that <hi>in &amp; by Him</hi> God is <hi>injoyed by us,</hi> even by ſo many as have Chriſt: For by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> all is
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:113054:34"/> 
                     <hi>removed,</hi> that kept us from God, and all is <hi>ſupplyed</hi> that may bring us to God, and make us injoy God; The Sufferings, Obedience, &amp; Interceſſion of Chriſt; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe Gods Wrath, &amp; ſatisfie Gods Juſtice, and ſoe brings the Perſon into full Favour with God, <hi>Math.</hi> 3. 17. he ſaith not with whome, but <hi>In whome I am well pleaſed;</hi> And the Spirit &amp; Holynes of Chriſt, workes out Corruption, &amp; workes in Holynes; and ſo there is brought about a Communion with God, &amp; Fruition of God, and ſo <hi>God walkes in them,</hi> and is their Father and God, they his Children &amp; People, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. latter end. And ſo in <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 13. Having <hi>by Faith</hi> got Chriſt to be theirs, though before they <hi>were affarr off,</hi> yet <hi>now are made neere;</hi> and ſo in the 19. <hi>Verſe. You are no more ſtrangers &amp; foreiners, but Citizens with the Saints &amp; of the houshould of God:</hi> Hence is that <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 11. <hi>Not onely ſo, but we alſo joy in God through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt by whom we have now received the atonement;</hi> there is Joy in God through Chriſt, therefore by Chriſt God is enjoyed; Now, where God is enjoyed; <hi>All wants muſt be ſupplyed,</hi> and <hi>All deſires allayed;</hi> For God is an Infinite Goodnes, therefore, they can want nothing, that have him; As they cannot want Light that have the Sunn, or Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that have the Ocean, becauſe there is a ſufficiency of Light in the Sunn, &amp; of Water in the Ocean:</p>
                  <p>Now <hi>God is Alſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, Gen.</hi> 17. 1. This <hi>God</hi> hath clearely proved, by his Workes of Creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Providence, He of <hi>Nothing</hi> made ſeverall Things; and filled them all full; He gave Perfection to every Creature at firſt, ſo that it lacked nothing, and to the whole Creation, that is ment by <hi>ſeeing it was good &amp; very good,</hi> that is every Part was perfect, lacking nothing, and the Whole was very Compleate &amp; Full; He that filled the whole
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:113054:35"/> World that it lacked nothing, Cannot he fill Mans deſires? And ſo by his Providence he fills &amp; ſatisfies, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107. 9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 145. 16. And he had not made all Man-kind to ſeeke him, (as he did, <hi>Acts.</hi> 17. 26. 27.) if he could not ſatisfie them; for then he had made ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>thing in vaine; all the infinite deſires that are in Man-kind, after a cheife Good; by injoying which they may be happy, as they ſhew there is a God, ſo they teach that, that God can fully ſatisfie them all; and this is expreſſe; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. <hi>&amp; laſt. Fullnes of Ioy, Ioy;</hi> therefore Fruitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of Deſire, elſe noe <hi>Ioy; and full Ioy;</hi> therefore there is <hi>ſupply of all Wants,</hi> and <hi>alaye of all Deſires;</hi> God himſelfe is ſatisfied in himſelfe, elſe he were not God, and being able to ſatisfie himſelfe, who is an Infinite being, he can much more ſatisfie Man that is but of a finite being; Since therefore <hi>Chriſt</hi> brings us into <hi>Gods Preſence</hi> as <hi>Eph.</hi> 3. 12. <hi>By him we have acceſſe,</hi> that is he is <hi>Gods Emiſſary,</hi> ſent from God to bring Beleevers into Gods Preſence &amp; ſo to injoy God (as the word ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies in Greeke) it muſt needs followe; That <hi>Every one that injoyeth Chriſt,</hi> muſt be <hi>Satisfied,</hi> and have <hi>All de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires alayed;</hi> Becauſe with Chriſt, <hi>God is had,</hi> and ſo <hi>All fulnes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the better clearing this <hi>Point;</hi> Conſider we in <note place="margin">In what reſpects, or how a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers nor thirſts.</note> 
                     <hi>What Reſpects,</hi> or <hi>How</hi> this can be true; That the <hi>Beleever never hungers nor thirſts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is true, in ſome degree in this Life; and fully &amp; compleately in the <hi>Life to Come.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt in this Life, it is true, in ſome degree; That he that <hi>Beleeves in Chriſt;</hi> hath all his wants <hi>ſupplyed,</hi> &amp; ſo all his deſires <hi>alayed;</hi> And that in a Three-fold <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. In reſpect of <hi>Sinne;</hi> He that beleeves in Chriſt,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:113054:35"/> ſhall not hunger nor thirſt <hi>after Sinne.</hi> This is the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Hunger &amp; Thirſt of an Unbeleever; Therefore <hi>Sinns</hi> are called <hi>Luſts,</hi> becauſe they are the appetites &amp; deſires of Unbeleevers; The Unbeleever, as truely wants &amp; deſires after, the <hi>Commiſſion of Sinne,</hi> ſome or other, according as he is carryed by Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Condition, Cuſtome, Company, or Tenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as the hungry or thirſty Man doth after Meate, or Drinke, <hi>Pro.</hi> 4. 16. <hi>They ſleepe not except they have done miſcheife;</hi> therefore it is, that they are ſo eager <hi>upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Sinne, Pro.</hi> 1. 16 <hi>Their feete run to evill;</hi> ſo 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 4. For there is a Nature in every Unbeleever; that is ſatisfied &amp; up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held by commiting <hi>Sinne,</hi> as our Nature is by Eating and Drinking, therefore <hi>It luſts, after evill; Iames.</hi> 4. 5. But now, <hi>He that Beleeves in Chriſt;</hi> is not thus to <hi>Sinne;</hi> The <hi>Body of Sinne is deſtroyed in him, Rom.</hi> 6. 6. therefore, he ſerves not, and ſo ſeekes nor <hi>Sinne;</hi> For he is ſaid to be <hi>Dead to Sinne Verſe.</hi> 7. therefore he deſires not after <hi>Sinne;</hi> Hence, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 5. <hi>The Beleever</hi> (who is deſcribed by his inſeperable Property to be after the Spirit) <hi>minds the Things of the Spirit,</hi> that is, and not <hi>the Things of the Flesh;</hi> The Unbeleever minds fleshly things; as a Woman that is with Child her eyes are ſtill on it if it be preſent, or elſe her Phant'ſy runns after it; But the <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever,</hi> lives the <hi>Life of Chriſt;</hi> and hath <hi>Chriſt dwelling in him,</hi> therefore he muſt doe as <hi>Chriſt did;</hi> that is, <hi>not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire Sinning,</hi> but to <hi>ſuppreſſe it</hi> as 1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3. 8. and <hi>Verſe.</hi> 9. <hi>He is made pertaker of the ſeede of God,</hi> therefore <hi>ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ſinne;</hi> that is, ſo farr as he is pertaker of that, there is a <hi>Nature in every Beleever;</hi> which is <hi>contrary</hi> to Sinne, <hi>He pertakes of the Divine Nature</hi> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 4. therefore wants not, nor ſeekes any ſatisfaction by Sinne; but the <hi>Contrary;</hi> He luſts after <hi>Holynes</hi> (as in the former Place is ſaid;
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:113054:36"/> 
                     <hi>minds the things of the Spirit; &amp; luſts againſt Sinne;</hi> as <hi>Gall.</hi> 5. 17. for it makes the Soule ſee miſery, in the Sinnes it deſired; and that happynes it ſought in Sinne; to ſee it &amp; ſeeke it in <hi>God &amp; Holynes:</hi> Now in reſpect of this the <hi>Doctrine</hi> is true; <hi>That in every Beleever there is no Hunger;</hi> becauſe the Nature is deſtroyed and ſo the appetite: Indeede there is an old Nature remaining in part in the <hi>Beleever,</hi> &amp; ſhall be in him as long as he lives, and that deſires after Sinne, which is ment by the <hi>Flesh its luſting againſt the Spirit, Gall.</hi> 5. 17. but there is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other <hi>Nature</hi> which is <hi>in him,</hi> that doth <hi>not luſt,</hi> in which regard he is ſaid not to deſire Sinne; So that the <hi>alaye</hi> of theſe deſires, is but in part &amp; ſome degree in this Life. As this is true in <hi>Reſpect of Sinne;</hi> So is it true:</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In <hi>Reſpect of the lawfull things of this World;</hi> as <hi>Life</hi> and things tending there to, Pleaſures, Honours, Profits, &amp;c. He that beleeves in Chriſt, ſhall not hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger &amp; thirſt after theſe, As is cleare in <hi>Zaccheus;</hi> who ſo thirſted after Riches, that he defrauded, oppreſt, withheld unjuſtly; yet having <hi>beleeved in Chriſt;</hi> he gives away halfe to the Poore; and tenders to reſtore foure-fold <hi>to all that he had wronged, Luke.</hi> 19. 8. Therefore the <hi>Beleevers Acts.</hi> 2. 44, 45. <hi>ſould their Goods &amp; Lands,</hi> &amp; committed them to the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> diſpoſe in good uſes, Thus <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 14. <hi>The World is crucified to me,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul)</hi> and ſo not coveted nor deſired, as a withered flower is not; therefore <hi>Paul</hi> had all appetite to this Lyfes Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent <hi>alayed;</hi> onely for ſome <hi>ſpirituall reſpects,</hi> Viz. the <hi>Churches good,</hi> he deſired <hi>to abyde in this Life Phillip,</hi> 23. 24. for all his overweaning opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of their excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy, are rectified, and he is made ſee, the Emptines, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty, Inſufficiency of them; that he cannot much regard them. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 16. <hi>Knowe</hi> (that is eſteeme
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:113054:36"/> and regard) <hi>no man after the flesh,</hi> that is in regard of Carnall Excellencies, and he ſees ſo much Satisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and Excellency in God, that he cannot much deſire them, as He cannot the Candle light, that hath the Sunns light; As <hi>Peter</hi> by the <hi>Glory of Chriſts Transfigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> was taken off from the Contents in the World, and therefore deſired to ſtay in the Mount with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> therefore, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 6. <hi>Godlynes with Content,</hi> (with <hi>Selfe-ſufficiency</hi> as the word is) <hi>is great gaine;</hi> there is a <hi>Selfe-ſufficiency</hi> in <hi>Godlynes,</hi> and therefore there is a modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in deſire to all outward things, for he knowes they be not of much concernment <hi>Luke.</hi> 12. 15. &amp; he knowes that they are not gort by our caring for them, but rather by our not caring; But <hi>God cares &amp; gives ſufficient, Verſe.</hi> 25. 30. Indeede <hi>Beleevers</hi> have &amp; may have ſome deſires after the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; <hi>Chriſt</hi> teacheth us to pray <hi>Give us this Day our dayly Bread;</hi> But it is nothing ſuch as it is in Unbeleevers, Its not the Principall &amp; Cheife Good: But as the baite &amp; refreſhment at an Inn, which one that travailes to an other Place, takes for his neceſſary refreſhment, therefore <hi>Beleevers</hi> are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt by <hi>Their leaving their Country</hi> and <hi>not returning when they might, Heb.</hi> 11. 13. <hi>to</hi> 17. This <hi>Alaye of Hunger,</hi> comes from the former, for the ſame Nature that had appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite to Sinne, ſent forth inordinate appetites to the things of this World: which Nature being deſtroyed the Deſire ceaſeth. As it is true in theſe Reſpects; So:</p>
                  <p n="3">3. In <hi>Reſpect of Grace &amp; true Happynes:</hi> The <hi>Beleever in Chriſt,</hi> in this Life, <hi>ſhall not hunger nor thirſt after Grace, &amp; true Happynes:</hi> For the underſtanding this, Ye muſt knowe that none doe ſo deſire <hi>Grace &amp; true Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynes,</hi> as the <hi>Beleever doth,</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 2. 3. and he never <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired it</hi> before he <hi>beleeved;</hi> ſo much as he doth after;
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:113054:37"/> as is cleare in <hi>David, ſo in Paul</hi> who had <hi>ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g earneſt Thirſts</hi> after <hi>Grace,</hi> as appeares <hi>by thoſe expreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> he uſeth, <hi>I beate downe my Body: I ſo run tbat I may attaine &amp;c.</hi> And this <hi>God</hi> would have us doe; he hath Commanded to followe or hunt <hi>after Righteouſnes &amp;c.</hi> But the <hi>Beleever</hi> is ſaid not to hunger &amp; thirſt after it; In theſe <hi>Foure Regards.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe <hi>He that beleeves in Chriſt,</hi> ſhall never fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally or totally <hi>looſe Grace &amp; true Happynes</hi> Viz: <hi>Gods Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, Image, &amp; Fellowship</hi> which he hath got <hi>by Chriſt;</hi> Theſe things ſhall be in him as a <hi>Spring living &amp; ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up for ever, Iohn.</hi> 4. 14. and not as a Pond which may in tyme be quite dryed up: and ſo the <hi>Beleever</hi> ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hunger &amp; thirſt after theſe things, as we doe after Meate &amp; Drinke, who though we have had it, yet over a while, are as deſtitute of it, and as fully want it as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver we did.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Not hungring,</hi> excludes not every deſire, but ſuch an one, as ſprings from a totall want of <hi>Grace;</hi> That this is true of the <hi>Beleever,</hi> is moſt cleare in <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> by <hi>many Places</hi> Viz: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89. 33. <hi>Nevertheleſſe my loving kindnes will I not utterly take from him; nor ſuffer my faythfullnes to fayle.</hi> Some may ſay this is ment of <hi>David</hi> for the Crowne; that his Seede ſhould never be wholy ſtript of it for ever: true; but not onely ſo, for <hi>Eſay,</hi> 55. 3. every Beleever is promiſed <hi>The ſure Mercyes of David, Ier.</hi> 31. 3. <hi>I have loved thee with an everlaſting Love: Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 11. 20. <hi>The Gifts,</hi> that is <hi>the gift of faith,</hi> &amp; <hi>ſo of Chriſt with faith,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Calling,</hi> that is, <hi>Vocation,</hi> and ſo the <hi>drawing to beleeve;</hi> is <hi>without repentance;</hi> that is on <hi>Gods part: Where God hath begun a good worke he will perfect it, Phill.</hi> 1. 6.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> He that <hi>Beleeves in Chriſt,</hi> may in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect be ſaid <hi>not to hunger after Grace,</hi> Becauſe he <hi>poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth,</hi> and hath <hi>in himſelfe,</hi> and of <hi>his owne,</hi> that which
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:113054:37"/> is aboundantly able, <hi>to ſupply</hi> all his wants, <hi>&amp; ſatisfie</hi> all his deſires; there is a <hi>ſpring in him Iohn.</hi> 4. 14. how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he may ſtand in neede of <hi>Grace,</hi> yet he hath as his owne, what may give a <hi>full ſupply;</hi> and all his deſires are <hi>virtually ſatisfied,</hi> in that he cannot deſire, what, he hath not to ſatisfie; He hath Two Store-houſes, Firſt <hi>Chriſt, In whome are hid all the treaſures of Wiſdome &amp; Knowledge, Coll</hi> 2. 3. <hi>and in whome dwelleth the fullnes of the God-head bodily Verſe</hi> 9. And Secondly he hath <hi>All the Promiſes,</hi> wherein there is <hi>All fullnes,</hi> and wherein God hath given him. <hi>All things that pertaine to life &amp; godlines</hi> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 3. 4. He is ſaid to have <hi>Rivers in him, Iohn.</hi> 7. 37. that is a continuall Streame of Satisfaction, able to fill up all wants; He cannot be ſaid to hunger becauſe he hath that in him, which is able to alaye his hunger; and when ever he will, he may take what ever his Soule can deſire. as <hi>Paul Rom.</hi> 7. 24. <hi>had deſires,</hi> which he preſently <hi>ſatisfies himſelfe in Verſe.</hi> 25. and <hi>gives thankes to God;</hi> And that there is ever a <hi>ſupply,</hi> appeares in this; that in his very want &amp; deſire, there is ſome Content, and ſtay to his Soule, therefore there is ſome ſupply.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> They are ſaid not to hunger, becauſe there is a Fullnes, <hi>Viae,</hi> not <hi>Patriae,</hi> ſuch a <hi>Fullnes,</hi> as ſuites their preſent Condition; a <hi>Comparative,</hi> though not an abſolute fullnes; Therefore the Saintes ſpeake of a Fullnes <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36. 8. 9. <hi>They ſhall be aboundantly ſatisfied with the fatnes of thy houſe,</hi> and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63. 5. <hi>My Soule ſhall be ſatisfied as with marrow &amp; fatnes;</hi> Such a fullnes, &amp; ſatisfieing, as they are capable of in this Life; For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, a Child may be ſaid to be a luſty ſtrong Child, whoſe ſtrength is nothing, in reſpect of the ſtrength of a Man, to which he may after attaine; So <hi>Beleevers,</hi>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:113054:38"/> have Satisfaction ſuteable to their Condition, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to the State wherein they are, a fullnes of Grace in regard of parts, though not of degrees, a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction according to their Capacity, though not ſo abſolute, as they ſhall one Day be capable off.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fourthly,</hi> They are fully ſatisfied in this Life, Becauſe they have <hi>All Things actually in Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>really by Faith;</hi> whoever <hi>Beleeves in Chriſt,</hi> hath all things actually in him: <hi>Coll.</hi> 2. 10. <hi>They are Compleate in him,</hi> There is in <hi>Chriſt</hi> a Fullnes of <hi>Grace &amp; Glory,</hi> and <hi>All</hi> that is in <hi>Chriſt</hi> is theirs, and they have it in him; <hi>He being full,</hi> they may truely be ſaid <hi>to be full:</hi> Chriſt not hungering and thirſting, they may truely be ſaid not to hunger or thirſt; Chriſt being fully ſatisfied, they are ſaid to be fully ſatisfied; For Chriſt ſtands in their ſtead, and poſſeſſeth all things in their name &amp; right; Chriſt was their Subſtitute, and that which is done to him, may be truely ſaid, to be done to them; as a Man who hath his debt fully payed to his Subſtitute, though he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it not by his owne hand, yet may truely acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſatisfaction, becauſe the other is his Receiver on his behalfe; So <hi>Beleevers</hi> may be ſaid, to have for the ſupply of all their wants; becauſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a fullnes, that they out of his fullnes, may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a full ſupply.</p>
                  <p>And further, as they have actually a compleate full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in Chriſt, Soe they have really <hi>that fullnes by Faith;</hi> In Chriſt, <hi>He that beleeves, hath everlaſting Life; Iohn.</hi> 3. 16. 36. <hi>everlaſting life,</hi> admitts not of hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger &amp; thirſt, <hi>hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pleate ſatisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> ſo <hi>faith brings in really a ſupply of all;</hi> as <hi>God</hi> hath all things to come, <hi>preſent,</hi> by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his <hi>Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitnes &amp; Eternity;</hi> ſo hath <hi>a beleever by faith, which is the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of things not ſeene, Heb,</hi> 11. 1. as <hi>Abraham had Chriſts day</hi>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:113054:38"/> 
                     <hi>preſent to him;</hi> And they are growing up to <hi>Perfection</hi> dayly; as the Child increaſeth dayly; for by <hi>Vertue</hi> of their <hi>Vnion to Christ.</hi> they receive of <hi>His fullnes,</hi> in the uſe of the <hi>Meanes; Iohn.</hi> 1. 16. growing up by the <hi>Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> towards <hi>Perfection;</hi> not onely a perfection of Parts (for that is at firſt received) but of <hi>Degrees, Eph.</hi> 4. 12. 13. As the Branch from the Roote, ſucks more &amp; more Sapp, or the Child from the Nurſe, or Body fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Head &amp; Stomack by which it growes up to full Stature; ſo that they be going to that <hi>Fullnes,</hi> which is in <hi>Heaven;</hi> wherein all deſires ſhall be <hi>ſatisfied.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In theſe <hi>Reſpects</hi> it is true in this Life; in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure &amp; degree.</p>
                  <p>Secondly in the <hi>Life to Come,</hi> it is <hi>Perfectly &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleately true;</hi> Every <hi>Beleever</hi> then ſhall have <hi>All wants ſupplyed, all deſires, alayed:</hi> All the aboundance of Good that the Soule is capable off, ſhall be there, <hi>fully ſupply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</hi> and ſo, all deſires muſt ceaſe when there is a <hi>full Fruition;</hi> Therefore it is called <hi>Ioy, Math.</hi> 25. 21. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is a full fruition of all deſirable Good, and they be ſaid to enter into it; to ſhew that it is ſo full &amp; large that it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not enter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but <hi>they enter it,</hi> &amp; ſo <hi>they are</hi> every way filled with it: As the Sea cannot be Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tayned in a ſmalle Ueſſell which may enter into it &amp; be filled as full as it can hold, yea ſwallowed up of it; ſo ſhall they be fully ſupplyed, and have more then they neede or can receive, and he that enters into an infinite Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, muſt needs have his finite Appetite fully ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17. <hi>laſt. When I awake</hi> (that is, am raiſed up out of the Duſt, at the laſt Day, for Death is called a Sleepe, and ſo <hi>Reſurrection an awaking) I ſhall be ſatisfied,</hi> therefore, no Hunger, no Thirſt; and it muſt be ſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of that where with we be ſatisfied; Viz: Gods
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:113054:39"/> Likenes, that is, <hi>God Him-ſelfe &amp; his Glory; Gods Face</hi> (as in the former words) <hi>it ſhall be veiwed;</hi> that is, there ſhall be a full &amp; cleare fruition of God, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 12. <hi>Then I ſhall ſee Face to Face, and know even as alſo I am knowne:</hi> Therefore if God can give full Satisfaction, it ſhall then be had; for then ſhall that fully be made good, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3. 19. <hi>That ye might be filled with the fullnes of God; All the fullnes of God,</hi> ſo far as ye are capable: If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there be enough in God, there then ſhall be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough: Thus, in the <hi>Life to Come,</hi> He that <hi>beleeves in Chriſt,</hi> ſhall have all wants <hi>ſupplied,</hi> &amp; all deſires <hi>alayed;</hi> becauſe he ſhall fully &amp; perfectly injoy God, and ſo perfect Happynes: Then all deſires to Sinne, ſhall be perfectly quelled, (for that all Sinne ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleately purged out) Then all neede &amp; deſire of the Creature in this World, ſhall be quite removed; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God ſhall be in ſtead of all, as the Sunn is in ſtead of a Candle, and the Ocean in ſtead of a Dropp 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 28. <hi>God ſhall be All in All;</hi> Meate, Drinke, Cloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Honour, Wealth Pleaſure Friends, <hi>and All, Mark.</hi> 12. 25. Then all deſires after <hi>Grace,</hi> ſhall be fully ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; becauſe there ſhall be a <hi>Perfection of all Grace,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of meaſures &amp; degrees, ſo much <hi>Grace</hi> ſhall be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed, as is deſired, or needed: Thus he that <hi>Beleeves in Chriſt, ſhall never hunger nor thirſt;</hi> becauſe <hi>God</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines to <hi>alaye his deſires</hi> ſo ſoone as <hi>he beleeves,</hi> and never leaves till <hi>He</hi> hath brought him to the <hi>full Fruition</hi> of all deſirable <hi>Good</hi> in the <hi>Heavens.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="1" type="application">
                  <head>USES. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſes. </seg>
                     </label> 
                  </head>
                  <p>Firſt, for <hi>Instruction &amp; Comfort</hi> to all that <hi>truely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1. <hi>For In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Comfort.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>in Chriſt</hi> (What it is <hi>truely to Beleeve?</hi> I opened in opening the <hi>Second Doctrine;</hi> where I ſhewed, It is not a
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:113054:39"/> groundles &amp; ſlight Conceite that <hi>Chriſt dyed for us;</hi> but an <hi>entertayning &amp; receiving Chriſt in all his Offices</hi> a <hi>full re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning ones Selfe to Him;</hi> Covenanting to be <hi>ordered &amp;</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Comfort for Beleev<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ers in two perticulers</note> 
                     <hi>guided by Him in all Things)</hi> to ſuch heere is <hi>Inſtruction &amp; Comfort;</hi> and that, In theſe Two Perticulers.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, <hi>You that beleeve in Chriſt;</hi> ſhall never totally or finally fall away from <hi>God &amp; Grace,</hi> ſo as wholly, or for ever to looſe <hi>them;</hi> (a Comfortable Point in theſe dangerous ſeducing &amp; declining Tymes) For he that once beleeves in Chriſt; ſaith <hi>Chriſt</hi> in my Text, <hi>ſhall never hunger nor thirſt;</hi> that is, ſhall never be wholy without <hi>God &amp; Grace, Chriſt &amp; Happynes,</hi> (as ye have heard in opening of the Point) Therefore, whatever appearances there may be, through the Subtilty of carnall Reaſon &amp; Satans Suggeſtions. <hi>Be thou aſſured,</hi> that having once <hi>beleeved in Christ,</hi> thou ſhalt never be wholly <hi>deſtitute</hi> of God &amp; Grace; for then thou muſt hunger &amp; thirſt; which <hi>Chriſt ſaith,</hi> ſhall never be:</p>
                  <p>Neither is that of weight againſt this <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mfortable Truth</hi> that Some object: So long <hi>as one beleeveth</hi> he ſhall <hi>never looſe wholly God &amp; Grace;</hi> But one that <hi>beleeveth</hi> may looſe his Faith; and then looſe God &amp; Grace wholly: This I ſay; is of no weight; For, though one may looſe the uſe of Faith for ſome tyme; Yet <hi>None that Beleeve,</hi> can ever <hi>wholly</hi> looſe Faith, nor any other ſaving Grace, as hath been ſhowed in the opening of this Point; and ſo as, he can never wholly looſe Faith, ſo neither can he ever looſe Chriſt or Grace; If the <hi>Covenant</hi> did run thus; That he that beleeves, ſo long as he beleeves, ſhall never fall away; But yet he might looſe all Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving, and ſo fall away; then were not that true; <hi>Iſay.</hi> 55 3. For with <hi>Every Beleever</hi> God makes an <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Covenant;</hi> Even the <hi>Sure Mercyes of David;</hi>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:113054:40"/> Now how were the Covenant <hi>Everlaſting,</hi> or the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy <hi>Sure;</hi> if that he might <hi>wholy</hi> looſe Faith, and ſo looſe God, &amp; all Grace? Surely that <hi>Place</hi> expreſly teacheth That when any one <hi>Beleeveth;</hi> God makes with him a <hi>Covenant,</hi> that ſhall <hi>Laſt for Ever;</hi> and beſtowes on him <hi>Mercy,</hi> that is <hi>Sure;</hi> and therefore he cannot be diſappointed; <hi>He that once beleeves</hi> muſt be <hi>for ever Gods,</hi> and never ſo fall as to <hi>miſſe Heaven;</hi> For <hi>Chriſt hath pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for All that beleeve,</hi> that <hi>They ſhould be with him, &amp; ſee his Glory, Iohn.</hi> 17. 20. 24.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Sonnes of God</hi> (and ſo is every one that <hi>Beleev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, Iohn.</hi> 1. 12.) muſt be <hi>Like Chriſt,</hi> when <hi>He appeares at the Laſt Day,</hi> 1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3. <hi>r.</hi> 2. Therefore, <hi>He that beleeveth, muſt be ſaved,</hi> and can <hi>never</hi> wholy looſe God or Grace; And therefore it is, that <hi>He that once Beleeves</hi> can never wholy <hi>looſe his Faith,</hi> becauſe to the end <hi>He may never looſe God or Grace,</hi> God preſerves <hi>Faith</hi> in him, and <hi>by that Faith</hi> preſerves him in Grace &amp; Favour with God, till he come to inherite Glory, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 4. 5. <hi>Who are kept by the Power of God through Faith &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, <hi>You that beleeve in Chriſt;</hi> ſhall have <hi>All your deſires alayed, All your wants ſupplyed, &amp; your Soules ſatisfied fully</hi> in this Life: 1. Your ſinfull deſires to Sinne, &amp; the Worlds Vanityes; theſe ſhall be alayed, by removing the Cauſe of them; Viz: Originall Corruption, the Vanity of your Minds &amp; Hearts: Your Soules ſhall be purged from thoſe ill Humors, which make you Hunger after this Trash; and ſhall be put in right frame, and you made to <hi>Hunger</hi> after <hi>good &amp; wholſome Things;</hi> Viz: <hi>Gods Favour &amp; Holynes, Gall.</hi> 5. 24. <hi>&amp; Chap.</hi> 6. 14. Examine your Selves well, and ye ſhall find, that ye doe not ſo hunger after theſe Things as ye did, and be ye ſure that ye ſhall doe it leſſe &amp; leſſe, till at
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:113054:40"/> laſt, ye ſhall be quite freed from that vaine Deſire: For thoſe many <hi>Exhortations</hi> in <hi>Scripture,</hi> to <hi>Mortifie thoſe Affections,</hi> and to <hi>Lay them downe;</hi> as <hi>Eph</hi> 4. 22. 23. 24. <hi>&amp; Coll.</hi> 3. 2. 5. doe include <hi>Promiſes</hi> (upon your indeavor) that it ſhall be done; as may be gathered from <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 12 14. where <hi>God promiſeth</hi> that ſhall be, which he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts to: Yea <hi>Gods Exhortations to Beleevers,</hi> are as his Word in Creation was, <hi>Operative.</hi> and working that which he Calls for, and Commands to be: Therefore doe ye but <hi>Exerciſe your Faith,</hi> and uſe the <hi>Meanes God hath appointed,</hi> and you ſhall have your ſinnfull &amp; trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome Deſires <hi>alayed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. So alſo, <hi>Your good &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendable Deſires after Grace &amp; Holynes;</hi> Thoſe ſhall <hi>be ſatisfied;</hi> Chriſt will fill you as full as ye can deſire, or contayne; Allready, ye have in you, the Store-houſe &amp; Treaſury of all Grace, the Spring is in you; <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in whome is all you neede, and therefore it is in him, that you may have it; <hi>He</hi> is yours, and from him ye may have whatever you neede doe but let downe the <hi>Bucket of Faith</hi> and drawe what <hi>Water</hi> ye deſire; <hi>He</hi> will never with-hold <hi>any Grace</hi> yee thirſt after, if ye truſt in him, and uſe the meanes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81. 10 <hi>He will fill the Mouth that is opened,</hi> and according to your hope in him, will he doe to you, he may defer you a while, to try the ſtrength of your <hi>Deſire,</hi> and of your <hi>Faith;</hi> but he will not with-hold ever, but <hi>ſatisfie your Deſire;</hi> Yea, he cannot with hold; for what you ſeeke by <hi>Faith in Him,</hi> and in the uſe of <hi>His meanes,</hi> he muſt give you, <hi>His Promiſe &amp; Office doe tye him</hi> to it; for <hi>He is your Spring of Grace</hi> to ſatisfie your thirſty Soules: And as a Mans owne Spring cannot with hold Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from him, when he comes to it, no more can <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Some wants ye ſhall have ſo long as ye live heere;
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:113054:41"/> but yet there ſhall be a ſatisfieing, &amp; filling up, though not filled up; as the Child is growing, though not fully growen, till he comes to Age: And ye ſhall have that fullnes, &amp; ſatisfaction; that is needfull &amp; requiſite for this Life, ſo much ye ſhall have: Therefore be Comforted; and ſinke not under the ſence of your wants; It is good to be ſenſible of <hi>ſpirituall wants,</hi> ſo as to ſeeke for ſupply; but it is folly &amp; unbeleefe, to be diſcouraged under them, ſince that ye have in hand &amp; doe poſſeſſe as your owne, that which is able &amp; ready to ſupply them all, if you uſe the meanes, Viz: <hi>Chriſt &amp; the Promiſes;</hi> Would not one thinke them Fooles, that complaine of Thirſt, and had a Spring of there owne, at their Doore?</p>
                  <p>Yea farther Conſider; that ye have <hi>actually all Full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes;</hi> Viz: <hi>In Chriſt &amp; the Promiſes;</hi> there is <hi>All Fullnes,</hi> what can you deſire that is not there? and it is all yours; So that in your Subſtitute, Treaſury, Srore houſe, Wardroope, there is <hi>actually</hi> all that you neede or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and it is all yours; <hi>For all is yours</hi> (as ye heard be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 21. and therefore the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeakes of <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Calvin</hi> on this <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> ſaith well: <hi>Si eges no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> habes fidem, Si habes fide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non eges.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Beleevers as poſſeſſing all things</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 10. <hi>&amp; Iam.</hi> 2. 5. ſtyles the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>rich in faith;</hi> that is not ment of abundance of <hi>Faith,</hi> (as ſometime the word is taken) but that <hi>by Faith</hi> they be <hi>Rich;</hi> So that every one that <hi>Beleeves</hi> is <hi>Rich</hi> by <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving;</hi> therefore poſſeſt of abundance (elſe none are called Rich) for the preſent injoying all that is needfull; <hi>and Heires of a Kingdome;</hi> for in the <hi>Life to come</hi> ye ſhall have a Satisfaction of all your Deſires: There ye ſhall have an <hi>abſolute Fullnes;</hi> all ſinnfull &amp; worldly Deſires ſhall be quite extinguiſht; all <hi>Holynes &amp; Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynes</hi> ſhall be perfectly adminiſtred; there is nothing neceſſary or deſirable for <hi>your Happynes,</hi> but ye ſhall
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:113054:41"/> enjoy it <hi>actually</hi> in the <hi>higheſt Degree;</hi> ye ſhall have your Wills to the full, no Want or Croſſe in any Deſire. <hi>God</hi> will ſay to you, as <hi>Herod</hi> to <hi>Herodias her Daughter Marke.</hi> 6. 22. 23. and better; not onely aske what you will <hi>to the Halfe of the Kingdome,</hi> but to the <hi>Whole,</hi> and it ſhall be <hi>granted you;</hi> Whatever <hi>Chriſt, Heaven, God</hi> can give, <hi>to fill you,</hi> you ſhall have ſo, far as you can receive. In a Word <hi>Ye ſhall be as Chriſt is</hi> 1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3. 2. So that if <hi>Chriſt is full, Ye ſhall be full;</hi> Wherefore be ye <hi>Comforted</hi> with theſe <hi>Things.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="application">
                  <head>2. USE. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> 
                  </head>
                  <p>For <hi>Tryall;</hi> Ye may by this try, whether <hi>ye Beleeve or</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">For Tryall</note> 
                     <hi>no:</hi> If yee <hi>Beleeve:</hi> ye doe <hi>not hunger &amp; thirſt:</hi> Thou that art <hi>not thus alayed</hi> in thy Deſires: Thou either doſt <hi>not Beleeve;</hi> Or doſt <hi>not exerciſe &amp; uſe Faith,</hi> Or <hi>Cbriſt ſaith not true:</hi> Ye that have gaping wide Deſires after Sinne, that feed on Sinne as an hungry Man, and drinke downe Iniquity as Water; ye doe not beleeve: Ye that as fully admire, ſeeke, &amp; delight in the Things of this World, as ye did formerly, and hunger &amp; thirſt <hi>cheifly</hi> after them, <hi>Ye Beleeve not:</hi> If your Deſires, goe out <hi>conſtantly,</hi> in an inordinate Way, to any of theſe Worlds Contents; Its a <hi>Signe</hi> you have <hi>not Faith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hence alſo a <hi>Diſcovery</hi> may be made; Both concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Meaſure,</hi> and <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of <hi>Faith;</hi> The ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger your <hi>Faith is,</hi> the leſſe is your hunger after the World and Sinne &amp;c. and according as you exerciſe <hi>Faith;</hi> will be the alaye of your deſires after ſuch things; You want the exerciſe of <hi>Faith,</hi> who cannot ſupply your wants, as you feele them; For <hi>Faith if exerciſed</hi> will draw from <hi>Chriſt</hi> and the <hi>Promiſes</hi> ſuch a fullnes as is convenient for this Life; It will ſhew you a <hi>Compleat fullnes in Chriſt</hi>
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:113054:42"/> as your owne; And where this is not, there <hi>Faith is weake,</hi> or not exerciſed as it ought to be.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="application">
                  <head>3. USE. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>3</label> 
                  </head>
                  <p>Shall be for <hi>Exhortation to Beleeve;</hi> Becauſe of the <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifite</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">For Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation.</note> that comes by it; This is <hi>Chriſts ayme</hi> in this <hi>Place:</hi> And this <hi>Vſe</hi> belongs, Firſt to ſuch of you, as yet never Beleeved: Secondly to ſuch as <hi>have,</hi> and <hi>doe</hi> in ſome meaſure <hi>Beleeve.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt to you that yet never Beleeved; That is <hi>never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1. <hi>To Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleevers.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Chriſt</hi> in all his Offices, and never gave up your Selves to whole Chriſt, as to your King, Preiſt, &amp; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet; But the moſt ye have done, is in a Generall manner to phanſy Chriſt dyed for you, and you ſhall be ſaved by him; which is not <hi>true Faith,</hi> as ye heard before: You, therefore that <hi>yet never rightly beleeved;</hi> be ye perſwaded to doe it, and that above all things: For why! what can doe you ſo much good as this? Is there any Thing in the World, can ſatisfie all your Deſires? Sinne doth not; Sinning alayes the Deſire of Sinne, no otherwiſe, then caſting on Oyle doth alaye the Fire, it increaſeth it; the more ye ſinne, the more ye deſire to ſinne: It is like the adminiſtring Wine in a Dropſy, Riches ſatisfie not, <hi>Ezekiell.</hi> 7. 19. <hi>Eccle.</hi> 5. 10. <hi>He that loveth Silver ſhall not be ſatisfied with Silver, nor he that loveth abundance, with increaſe,</hi> he ſpake it that had fully tryed it, and therefore the more to be regarded, And as it holdeth in Riches, So likewiſe in Honour, Pleaſure, or any Thing elſe, ye ſeeke after, and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect <hi>Beleeving.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That which is reported of <hi>Alexander,</hi> is to be found in every ones Heart, which a <hi>Philoſopher</hi> diſcovered in his, by this <hi>Queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> to him, <hi>When thou haſt Conquered Greece</hi>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:113054:42"/> 
                     <hi>what wilt thou doe?</hi> He anſwered, I will Conquer <hi>Aſia</hi> and the whole World; <hi>When that is done what wilt thou doe?</hi> I will (ſaith he) wish for another World to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer; thus unſatisfied was he by all his Honour: And thus is it with Men, both for Honour, Pleaſure &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Our Soules are made to enjoy <hi>God,</hi> therefore Covet an Infinite &amp; Eternall Good; which is ment by that <hi>Groping after God, Acts.</hi> 17. 27. Not that they ſeeke God <hi>as God,</hi> for ſo, that is true, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 11. <hi>There is none ſeeketh after God,</hi> but in that they ſeeke blindly after an Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite &amp; Eternall Good (which onely is <hi>God,</hi> though they thinke not ſo) they be ſaid to <hi>grope or feele after God</hi> and therefore reſt unſatisfied, in any finite or mortall good, reall or ſeeming: Our Soules are like the gape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Earth, full of Chinckes, and great Crannyes, which nothing in the World can fill &amp; ſatisfie, but the Ocean or Showers of <hi>Heaven, God Him ſelfe;</hi> hence is that reſtleſſnes that is in all Hearts: Whatever they have, even in this ſence, they are toſſed up &amp; downe, as the Sea, and not quiet: For ſo long as the Soule is in Deſire, it is in a reſtleſſnes, &amp; troubleſome Motion. And hence it is there be <hi>ſuch ſhiftings</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one thing to another, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Coveteouſnes to Prodigallity &amp;c. (though ye never have the witt to ſhift from the Creature to <hi>God,</hi> for then ye would be ſatisfied) becauſe in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ye be ſatisfied: yea, and God oft lets you have your Deſires, ſo much Wealth, Pleaſure, or Honour, as ye ſeeke, and yet ye be not ſatisfied, that ſo ye may knowe, there is nothing can ſatisfie but <hi>God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And this I aſſure you, if ye Beleeve not, (Marke it, for ye ſhall one Day remember, ye were told of it) ye ſhall ever hunger &amp; thirſt, and never be ſatisfied, and that is a great Miſery: as <hi>He that beleeves ſhall never,</hi> ſo
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:113054:43"/> you that beleeve not, ſhall ever hunger &amp; want, and never get Satisfaction, <hi>Pro.</hi> 13. 25. Therefore ſuch a Condition is diſcribed in <hi>Scripture</hi> by them that <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in the Fire,</hi> and for <hi>Vanity, Habuc.</hi> 2. 13. That <hi>feede on Ashes, Eſay.</hi> 44. 20. Follow the <hi>Eaſt Wind, Hoſea.</hi> 12. 1. Labour <hi>wholly in Vaine;</hi> as <hi>Eſay.</hi> 55. 2. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Difference twixt them that <hi>Beleeve,</hi> and thoſe who doe not Beleeve, <hi>Eſay.</hi> 65. 13. <hi>Gods Servants,</hi> that is, <hi>Beleevers; ſhall have Ioy,</hi> becauſe <hi>full Satisfaction;</hi> and ſo <hi>no hunger:</hi> Ye, that beleeve not, ſhall want, and ſo be ashamed, becauſe ye have not got that ye ſought:</p>
                  <p>In this Life, ye ſhall not be ſatisfied, and much leſſe in <hi>Hell;</hi> there is <hi>Paena Damni,</hi> ye ſhall be punished with loſſe &amp; want of what ye ſeeke: <hi>Dives;</hi> who was full of Honours &amp; Riches, and enjoyed a fullnes of all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Contentments, while he was in the World; yet this <hi>Dives,</hi> becauſe he was not a <hi>Beleever,</hi> he thirſted after a dropp of Water; and could not have that Thirſt alayed: There ſhall be continually <hi>Reniſus Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntatis,</hi> your wills ſhall ever incline unto this &amp; that good which ye want, but ſhall ever deſire, and never attaine to; It is a painefull thing, to hunger &amp; thirſt, and not to have to ſatisfie; the Poore knowe this: Oh! what is it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger &amp; thirſt, a Yeare together and never be ſatisfied? and what is it to doe ſo <hi>Ever?</hi> yet this, &amp; all this is, &amp; ſhall be your Caſe, <hi>who beleeve not in Chriſt;</hi> that is, doe not ſo receive him in <hi>All his Offices.</hi> as hath been opened.</p>
                  <p>But on the other ſide, if ye will <hi>Beleeve in Chriſt;</hi> yee ſhall <hi>never hunger nor thirſt,</hi> what would a hungry Man doe for this? will he not venter his Life? If ye will <hi>Beleeve,</hi> ye ſhall have a <hi>ſupply</hi> of all good things, and be as <hi>Deut.</hi> 33. 23. <hi>Satisfied with Favour, &amp; full of the</hi>
                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:113054:43"/> 
                     <hi>Bleſſing of the Lord.</hi> Ye neede not goe out as I may ſo ſay, but ſhall have of your owne, whatever you neede for Soule or Body: Ye may have outward Things, &amp; yet want more, or looſe them againe: But <hi>Beleeve,</hi> &amp; ye ſhall <hi>have all Good,</hi> and <hi>never looſe it:</hi> Ye deſire Joy, Heere is the <hi>Way</hi> to <hi>Full Ioy;</hi> ye muſt have full fruition of all Good, and that is <hi>onely</hi> had by <hi>Beleeving:</hi> Your deſires to Sinne ſhall be <hi>alayed;</hi> and <hi>new Deſires given you, &amp; ſatisfied;</hi> and that is <hi>all one,</hi> as if ye had them of Sinne, ſatisfied:</p>
                  <p>Therefore Conſider what the <hi>Prodigall ſaith, Luke.</hi> 15. 17. 18. <hi>In my Fathers Houſe is Bread enough; and I dye for Hunger:</hi> In <hi>God</hi> there is <hi>Fullnes</hi> enough of <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> and I am diſtracted through want of it: Reaſon then as the <hi>Prodigall did;</hi> Allas! I am heere, ready to <hi>famish,</hi> for <hi>want of Bread;</hi> How <hi>unſatisfied</hi> is my <hi>Soule?</hi> I follow after Wealth, Honours, &amp; Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and yet my <hi>Soule</hi> hungers &amp; thirſts; Why ſhould my <hi>Soule be famished heere;</hi> and <hi>perish heereafter?</hi> There is <hi>Bread enough</hi> in the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> In <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> I may have to <hi>ſupply</hi> all my wants, a <hi>Compleate Satisfaction:</hi> Why ſhould not <hi>I renounce my Selfe; Forſake my Sinne;</hi> and <hi>Goe to Chriſt?</hi> I will goe to <hi>Him,</hi> and <hi>Beleeve in Him:</hi> How great a Benifite would it be to have Meate or Drinke that would alaye Hunger &amp; Thirſt for <hi>Ever?</hi> This is had by <hi>Faith:</hi> This <hi>Argument</hi> perſwaded the <hi>Woman Iohn.</hi> 4. 14. 15. Let it perſwade you.</p>
                  <p>Ye have heard in the former <hi>Doctrine;</hi> That <hi>Any one, what Perſon ſoever, may by Beleeving get Chriſt:</hi> God in his <hi>Goſpel</hi> ſhutts out <hi>None,</hi> therefore be not kept from indeavoring to <hi>Beleeve</hi> by a Conceite, that ſuch a Sinner as thou ſhalt not be accepted, for any that come <hi>are Wellcome;</hi> Labour <hi>thou the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to Beleeve:</hi> and know
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:113054:44"/> that on theſe Tearmes, <hi>Perfect Happynes,</hi> is offered thee; For it is that <hi>onely</hi> which can <hi>ſatisfie</hi> all Deſires; and therefore, above all, <hi>Labour to Beleeve in Chriſt;</hi> If thou wilt not, thou <hi>refuſeſt Perfect Happynes;</hi> and ſhalt have perfect Miſery.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, This ſerves alſo for <hi>Exhortation,</hi> To <hi>You</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2. <hi>To Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>that have Beleeved:</hi> Gett <hi>more Faith,</hi> and exerciſe <hi>Faith more,</hi> So ſhall your Wants be <hi>ſupplyed,</hi> and Deſires <hi>ſatisfied,</hi> and this is the <hi>Way</hi> to have more freedome from ſinnfull &amp; worldly Deſires, and to have your fill of <hi>Grace, God, &amp; Happynes;</hi> you want ſo much, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you actually beleeve ſo <hi>little;</hi> For <hi>Beleeving</hi> brings <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> and the <hi>more ye Beleeve,</hi> the <hi>more full Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction:</hi> Be allwayes then in the uſe &amp; exerciſe of <hi>Faith,</hi> abound there with; <hi>Sathan</hi> above all things, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to hinder your growth in <hi>Faith;</hi> becauſe by that meanes he would keepe you in want; But learne you above all things, to labour to <hi>abound in Faith,</hi> for then ſhall you want nothing: Hence are there ſo many Exhortations &amp; Prayers made by the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for <hi>Beleevers abounding in Faith;</hi> For as they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe &amp; increaſe in <hi>Faith,</hi> ſo all Fullnes is farther con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed to them:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Faith</hi> is as the <hi>Bucket,</hi> which let downe fetcheth <hi>Water;</hi> and the oftner you let it downe, the more <hi>Water</hi> you have; The Exerciſe of <hi>Faith</hi> is as the turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Cock, which if turned, letts in Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; So <hi>Faith exerciſed,</hi> letts in all ſupply, and the more it is exerciſed, the greater is the ſupply; The more Faith, the more fullnes; If we want, the want is not from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but from our want of the exerciſe of <hi>Faith:</hi> Exerciſe <hi>Faith</hi> then, and you will never be <hi>pincht</hi> with Hunger or Thirſt, or be ſo <hi>perplext,</hi> as often
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:113054:44"/> ye are; But you ſhall enjoy a <hi>Heaven</hi> upon Earth; you ſhall have a ſweete <hi>Influence</hi> of all <hi>Grace,</hi> as faſt as your <hi>Soules</hi> can receive it; you ſhall enjoy the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> and the <hi>Favour of God,</hi> and be fully ſatisfied; All <hi>Supplyes</hi> are to be had <hi>onely from Chriſt;</hi> and all to be had <hi>from Chriſt, onely by Beleeving.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Faith Exerciſed</hi> doth Three Things. <note place="margin">Faith ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed, doth 3 Things.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, <hi>It Conveyes the Thing that is ſought;</hi> Therefore ſo oft in <hi>Scripture, It</hi> is made the <hi>Inſtrument</hi> of Convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of all Gods Bleſſings; By <hi>Faith Sarah received the promiſed Sonne: Heb</hi> 11. 11. So <hi>Gall.</hi> 3. 14. The <hi>Promiſe of the Spirit is received by Faith:</hi> It is <hi>Faith</hi> brings it: Therefore the <hi>Scripture</hi> makes <hi>Faith</hi> to <hi>Conveye</hi> the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done of Sinne,</hi> the <hi>healing Diſeaſes:</hi> and <hi>whatever it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeves, Math.</hi> 8. 13. (as ye heard before) For, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever <hi>Faith</hi> layes hold on, it makes it thine owne, be it ever ſo much: And.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, <hi>Vntill</hi> it hath Brought &amp; Conveyed the Thing, <hi>It gives Aſſurance that it ſhall be had,</hi> and ſo it gives Content &amp; Satisfaction in ſome meaſure as if it were had; As it did to <hi>Abraham</hi> for his <hi>Iſaac, Gen.</hi> 17. 17. it made him laugh, that is <hi>Ioy,</hi> (for it was another kind of laughing then <hi>Sarahs</hi> was; who laughed out of ſcorne of the thing ſpoken, as deeming it impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible &amp; therefore was ſhee rebuked) I ſay, <hi>Faith made Abrahamlaugh;</hi> that is <hi>Ioy</hi> in the <hi>Aſſurance</hi> of the <hi>thing:</hi> And ſo it made <hi>Hanna quiet,</hi> and eaſed her of her per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1. 10. 18. upon <hi>Her praying,</hi> ſhee <hi>Beleeving</hi> was <hi>Satisfied,</hi> untill ſhee had it; For <hi>Faith exerciſed,</hi> doth aſſure the Soule, the Thing deſired ſhall be had, in the beſt tyme &amp; manner.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, <hi>It preſents all fullnes &amp; deſirablenes,</hi> as that which ſhall be in due tyme poſſeſſed, &amp; enjoyed;
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:113054:45"/> It gives <hi>a glimps,</hi> of all that <hi>God hath Promiſed,</hi> or <hi>thou deſireſt; Faith</hi> leadeth thee to <hi>Heaven,</hi> and ſheweth thee the <hi>many Manſions,</hi> the <hi>Crowne of Glory,</hi> the <hi>glorious Roabes,</hi> the <hi>immortall Inheritance,</hi> the <hi>Kingdome</hi> that ſhall <hi>never be ſhaken,</hi> whatever is <hi>to Come, Faith</hi> gives the ſight of it <hi>before hand;</hi> looke as <hi>God did to Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Gen.</hi> 15. <hi>He ſhewed him that full Poſterity, &amp; Poſſeſſion</hi> that in <hi>due tyme, he ſhould have;</hi> So doth <hi>Faith; Heb.</hi> 11. 13. <hi>By faith they ſaw the things promiſed afarr off, &amp; were perſwaded of them, &amp; embraced them</hi> (or <hi>ſaluted them)</hi> that is as <hi>things preſent</hi> and <hi>enjoyed by them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now <hi>Faith</hi> doing thus; the more it is; the more it doth thus; as Fire heating, the more the Fire is, the more it heates; and the more it is exerciſed, the more it doth thus: For it is with <hi>Faith,</hi> as it is with any Skill Power, or Habit; if it be not uſed &amp; exerciſed; it doth nothing, he that hath it is never the better, there is no difference twixt him &amp; another, that hath noe ſuch thing: And this is the great folly of <hi>Beleevers</hi> that they grow not in, and exerciſe not their <hi>Faith;</hi> did they ſo, they could want no good thing: Therefore Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, what <hi>Increaſe</hi> can yeild ye ſo much <hi>Benifite,</hi> as the <hi>Increaſe of your Faith?</hi> what <hi>Exerciſe</hi> can doe ye ſo much good, as the <hi>Exerciſe of your Faith?</hi> Therefore, above all things, <hi>mind this:</hi> Doe ye as <hi>Hab.</hi> 2. 4. <hi>Live by your Faith:</hi> Let that be it whereby ye doe <hi>All Things,</hi> and paſſe <hi>All Tyme,</hi> let it be in <hi>Continuall Action</hi> in you, on <hi>All Occaſions:</hi> And I Aſſure you, <hi>Yee ſhall never Hunger nor Thirſt;</hi> But be <hi>free</hi> from all the <hi>Pinches</hi> and <hi>Pangs, Perplexities,</hi> and <hi>Troubles,</hi> that now ye un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der goe.</p>
                  <p>Thus; Ye have had the <hi>Pith &amp; Subſtance</hi> of this <hi>Text,</hi> In theſe <hi>Foure Doctrines.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:113054:45"/>
                  <p n="1"> 1. <hi>That Chriſt is the Bread of Life;</hi> that is, <hi>The one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; alſufficient Remedy of Mans Miſery.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>That the all &amp; onely Meanes appointed &amp; required by God, for the obtaining this Chriſt; is Comming to him;</hi> that is, <hi>Beleeving on Him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>That Every Perſon without any limitation or ſeclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, by Beleeving on Chriſt, may certainly obtaine Him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>That whoever Comes to Chriſt, or Beleeves in Chriſt, ſhall never hunger nor thirſt;</hi> that is, <hi>ſhall have all his Wants ſupplyed, and his Soule fully ſatisfied.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I Conclude all, with that of</p>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>Hoſea Chap, Laſt. Verſe. the Laſt.</bibl>
                     <q>Who is wiſe, &amp; he ſhall Vnderſtand theſe Things.</q>
                  </epigraph>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="Scripture_index">
            <pb facs="tcp:113054:46"/>
            <head>A TABLE of ſuch Scriptures, as receive Light in the precedent Matter.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>THE FIRST PART.</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">CAP.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">VERS.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">PAGE.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Gen: 3.</cell>
                     <cell>8. to 12.</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>15.</cell>
                     <cell>1, 2.</cell>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Deut: 4.</cell>
                     <cell>30.</cell>
                     <cell>38</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5.</cell>
                     <cell>23. to 29.</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Iudg: 15.</cell>
                     <cell>18.</cell>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ruth: 3.</cell>
                     <cell>18.</cell>
                     <cell>32</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1. Kings, 8.</cell>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2. Kings, 17.</cell>
                     <cell>13.</cell>
                     <cell>37</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Pſal: 41.</cell>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                     <cell>26</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>51.</cell>
                     <cell>3.</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>90.</cell>
                     <cell>11.</cell>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>119.</cell>
                     <cell>59, 128.</cell>
                     <cell>37</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Pro: 30.</cell>
                     <cell>12.</cell>
                     <cell>19</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ecleſ: 7.</cell>
                     <cell>26.</cell>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>9.</cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Eſaith, 1.</cell>
                     <cell>16, 17.</cell>
                     <cell>39</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>55.</cell>
                     <cell>1, 2.</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>59.</cell>
                     <cell>30.</cell>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ier: 2.</cell>
                     <cell>19.</cell>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                     <cell>3.</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6.</cell>
                     <cell>14.</cell>
                     <cell>1, 9</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>26.</cell>
                     <cell>3.</cell>
                     <cell>37</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Lam: 3.</cell>
                     <cell>40.</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mich: 7.</cell>
                     <cell>19.</cell>
                     <cell>38</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Math: 4.</cell>
                     <cell>17.</cell>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>11.</cell>
                     <cell>28.</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>21.</cell>
                     <cell>32.</cell>
                     <cell>29, 37</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>22.</cell>
                     <cell>3.</cell>
                     <cell>14. 36</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Marke, 6.</cell>
                     <cell>12.</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>10.</cell>
                     <cell>21, 22</cell>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Luke, 1</cell>
                     <cell>71, to 74.</cell>
                     <cell>38</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                     <cell>18, 19.</cell>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>13.</cell>
                     <cell>1, 2, 3.</cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>14.</cell>
                     <cell>16.</cell>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>15.</cell>
                     <cell>7.</cell>
                     <cell>39</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>11.</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Iohn, 3.</cell>
                     <cell>8.</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6.</cell>
                     <cell>29.</cell>
                     <cell>34</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>60, 66.</cell>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>16.</cell>
                     <cell>8.</cell>
                     <cell>7, 9, 21</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Acts, 2.</cell>
                     <cell>37.</cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>39.</cell>
                     <cell>36</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3.</cell>
                     <cell>19.</cell>
                     <cell>26</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>13.</cell>
                     <cell>39.</cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>16.</cell>
                     <cell>29, 30, 34.</cell>
                     <cell>16, 32</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>17.</cell>
                     <cell>30.</cell>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>26.</cell>
                     <cell>20.</cell>
                     <cell>38, 40</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>21.</cell>
                     <cell>38</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Rom: 1.</cell>
                     <cell>6, 7.</cell>
                     <cell>39</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3.</cell>
                     <cell>22, 25, 27, 28.</cell>
                     <cell>32</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>24.</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5.</cell>
                     <cell>20.</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>7.</cell>
                     <cell>9.</cell>
                     <cell>11, 23</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>8.</cell>
                     <cell>15.</cell>
                     <cell>5, 10, 21</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>9.</cell>
                     <cell>24, 25.</cell>
                     <cell>36</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>11.</cell>
                     <cell>26.</cell>
                     <cell>37</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:113054:46"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1. Cor: 1.</cell>
                     <cell>30.</cell>
                     <cell>38</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>11:</cell>
                     <cell>31.</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2. Cor: 4.</cell>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Gall: 3.</cell>
                     <cell>22.</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>23, 24.</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Eph: 1.</cell>
                     <cell>6.</cell>
                     <cell>31</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5.</cell>
                     <cell>14.</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1 Theſ: 4.</cell>
                     <cell>7.</cell>
                     <cell>39</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1. Tim: 1.</cell>
                     <cell>13.</cell>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>16.</cell>
                     <cell>36</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6.</cell>
                     <cell>12.</cell>
                     <cell>39</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2. Tim: 1.</cell>
                     <cell>9.</cell>
                     <cell>39</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Titus, 2.</cell>
                     <cell>14.</cell>
                     <cell>38</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Heb: 6.</cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell>37</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>11.</cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell>33</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>12.</cell>
                     <cell>18, to 22.</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>21.</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Iam: 4.</cell>
                     <cell>9, 10.</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1, Iohn, 4.</cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Rev: 22.</cell>
                     <cell>17.</cell>
                     <cell>12, 16, 31</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>THE SECOND PART.</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Gen: 3.</cell>
                     <cell>15.</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>17.</cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell>55</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>17.</cell>
                     <cell>75</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>41.</cell>
                     <cell>55, 57.</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>47.</cell>
                     <cell>14, 17, 20, 23.</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>50.</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Exod: 16.</cell>
                     <cell>3, 15, 16;</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Deut: 15.</cell>
                     <cell>12, 13.</cell>
                     <cell>41</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>33.</cell>
                     <cell>23.</cell>
                     <cell>72</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1. Sam: 1.</cell>
                     <cell>10, 18.</cell>
                     <cell>75</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2. Cron: 1.</cell>
                     <cell>15.</cell>
                     <cell>43</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Pſal: 16.</cell>
                     <cell>11.</cell>
                     <cell>56</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>17.</cell>
                     <cell>15.</cell>
                     <cell>63</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>34.</cell>
                     <cell>8, 9, 10.</cell>
                     <cell>53</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>36.</cell>
                     <cell>8, 9.</cell>
                     <cell>61</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>63.</cell>
                     <cell>5.</cell>
                     <cell>61</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>81.</cell>
                     <cell>10.</cell>
                     <cell>67</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>89.</cell>
                     <cell>33.</cell>
                     <cell>60</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>107.</cell>
                     <cell>9.</cell>
                     <cell>56</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>145,</cell>
                     <cell>16.</cell>
                     <cell>56</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Pro: 1.</cell>
                     <cell>16.</cell>
                     <cell>57</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Pro: 1.</cell>
                     <cell>24.</cell>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                     <cell>16.</cell>
                     <cell>57</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ecleſ: 5.</cell>
                     <cell>10.</cell>
                     <cell>70</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Eſa: 33.</cell>
                     <cell>22.</cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>44.</cell>
                     <cell>20.</cell>
                     <cell>72</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>49.</cell>
                     <cell>9, 10.</cell>
                     <cell>52, 53</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>55.</cell>
                     <cell>1, 2, 3.</cell>
                     <cell>53, 65, 72</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>65.</cell>
                     <cell>13.</cell>
                     <cell>72</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ier: 31.</cell>
                     <cell>14, 25.</cell>
                     <cell>53</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>50.</cell>
                     <cell>19.</cell>
                     <cell>ibid</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Hab: 2.</cell>
                     <cell>13.</cell>
                     <cell>72</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Math. 1.</cell>
                     <cell>23.</cell>
                     <cell>54</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3.</cell>
                     <cell>17.</cell>
                     <cell>55</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>8.</cell>
                     <cell>13.</cell>
                     <cell>37, 75</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>10.</cell>
                     <cell>12.</cell>
                     <cell>51</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>18.</cell>
                     <cell>11.</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>21.</cell>
                     <cell>31, 32.</cell>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>22.</cell>
                     <cell>11, 12, 13.</cell>
                     <cell>16, 43</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>25.</cell>
                     <cell>21.</cell>
                     <cell>63</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Marke, 6.</cell>
                     <cell>22, 23.</cell>
                     <cell>69</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>16.</cell>
                     <cell>15, 16.</cell>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:113054:47"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Luke, 2.</cell>
                     <cell>10, 34.</cell>
                     <cell>41, 50, 51</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                     <cell>19</cell>
                     <cell>41</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>7.</cell>
                     <cell>29, 30.</cell>
                     <cell>36</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>12.</cell>
                     <cell>15, 25, 30.</cell>
                     <cell>59</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>14.</cell>
                     <cell>16, 17, 24.</cell>
                     <cell>16, 36, 42</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>19.</cell>
                     <cell>14.</cell>
                     <cell>36</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Iohn, 1.</cell>
                     <cell>12.</cell>
                     <cell>15, 22, 54, 56</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3.</cell>
                     <cell>14, 15.</cell>
                     <cell>18, 39, 40</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>16, 36.</cell>
                     <cell>62</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>19.</cell>
                     <cell>36, 44</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                     <cell>12, 14.</cell>
                     <cell>60, 54, 73</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6.</cell>
                     <cell>50, to 57.</cell>
                     <cell>6, 11</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>44.</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>67, 68.</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>12.</cell>
                     <cell>39, 40, 47, 48.</cell>
                     <cell>18, 50</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>14.</cell>
                     <cell>19.</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell>7, 8.</cell>
                     <cell>5, 25</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Acts, 2.</cell>
                     <cell>38.</cell>
                     <cell>35</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>9.</cell>
                     <cell>6, 11, 17.</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>13.</cell>
                     <cell>47, 48</cell>
                     <cell>17, 36, 44</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>16.</cell>
                     <cell>30, 31.</cell>
                     <cell>35</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>17.</cell>
                     <cell>20, 27, 30,</cell>
                     <cell>35, 36, 71</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>22.</cell>
                     <cell>16.</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Rom: 3.</cell>
                     <cell>11.</cell>
                     <cell>71</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>22, 23.</cell>
                     <cell>18. 41</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                     <cell>21, 22.</cell>
                     <cell>37</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5.</cell>
                     <cell>11.</cell>
                     <cell>55.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                     <cell>24, 25.</cell>
                     <cell>61</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>8.</cell>
                     <cell>5.</cell>
                     <cell>57</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>11.</cell>
                     <cell>29.</cell>
                     <cell>60</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1. Cor: 1.</cell>
                     <cell>30.</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>13.</cell>
                     <cell>12.</cell>
                     <cell>64</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>15.</cell>
                     <cell>17, 28.</cell>
                     <cell>50, 64</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2. Cor: 2.</cell>
                     <cell>15, 16.</cell>
                     <cell>51</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5.</cell>
                     <cell>16.</cell>
                     <cell>58</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Gall: 3:</cell>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                     <cell>18, 75</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5.</cell>
                     <cell>6, 17.</cell>
                     <cell>25. 58</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6.</cell>
                     <cell>14.</cell>
                     <cell>58</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Eph: 2.</cell>
                     <cell>13, 19.</cell>
                     <cell>55</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>12.</cell>
                     <cell>56</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3.</cell>
                     <cell>17, 19.</cell>
                     <cell>54, 64</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                     <cell>8, 12.</cell>
                     <cell>5, 63</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>23, 24, 25.</cell>
                     <cell>67</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Phil: 1.</cell>
                     <cell>23, 24.</cell>
                     <cell>58</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3.</cell>
                     <cell>8. 9.</cell>
                     <cell>34</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Col: 1.</cell>
                     <cell>14, 21, 22.</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2.</cell>
                     <cell>3. 9. 10.</cell>
                     <cell>61, 62</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3.</cell>
                     <cell>25.</cell>
                     <cell>67</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1. Theſ:. 5</cell>
                     <cell>9.</cell>
                     <cell>44</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2. Theſ: 1.</cell>
                     <cell>7, 8.</cell>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1. Tim: 6.</cell>
                     <cell>6.</cell>
                     <cell>59</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Heb: 3.</cell>
                     <cell>19.</cell>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>7.</cell>
                     <cell>25, 26.</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>10.</cell>
                     <cell>19, to 23.</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>11.</cell>
                     <cell>11.</cell>
                     <cell>75</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>13, 17.</cell>
                     <cell>59, 76</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Iames, 2.</cell>
                     <cell>5.</cell>
                     <cell>68</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                     <cell>5.</cell>
                     <cell>57</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1. Pet: 1.</cell>
                     <cell>4, 5.</cell>
                     <cell>66</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                     <cell>57</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2. Pet: 1.</cell>
                     <cell>3, 4.</cell>
                     <cell>57, 61</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1. Iohn. 3.</cell>
                     <cell>1, 2.</cell>
                     <cell>66, 69</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>8, 9.</cell>
                     <cell>57</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Rev: 6.</cell>
                     <cell>15, 16, 17</cell>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>7.</cell>
                     <cell>16, 17.</cell>
                     <cell>53</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>22.</cell>
                     <cell>17.</cell>
                     <cell>42</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
